<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Practical discourses upon the morality of the Gospel</title>
            <author>Jenks, Sylvester, 1656?-1714.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 202 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 99 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46799</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J630D</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220354</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831758</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831758</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36225</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46799)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36225)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2126:40)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Practical discourses upon the morality of the Gospel</title>
                  <author>Jenks, Sylvester, 1656?-1714.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>194+ p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed M DC XCIX. [1699]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Silvester Jenks.</note>
                  <note>Includes contents.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The morality of the Gospel.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: all after p. 194 lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Gospels --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36225:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36225:1"/>
            <p>Practical DISCOURSES UPON THE Morality OF THE <hi>GOSPEL.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed MDCXCIX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:36225:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36225:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>MOrality is my Buſineſs. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality Improv'd, Exalted, and Rais'd nearer Heaven by Religion. If Controverſie ever happens to lye fairly in my way, I ſhall as fairly paſs it by, without ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any Notice of it. I am not at all deſirous to Diſpute with my Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; but to do him good: Which I believe is ſeldom done by Arguing and Diſputing.</p>
            <p>The beſt thing that Controverſie can do, is to ſhew us clearly, which is the True Religion: And I preſume All Parties are Agreed, that This is a very Neceſſary Point; or otherwiſe they would not think it worth their
<pb facs="tcp:36225:3"/>quarrelling ſo fiercely and ſo obſtinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly about it. But yet, when This is done, we are only beginning the Great Work of our Salvation. The Beſt <hi>Religion</hi> in the World can never Save us, without a conſtant Practice of the Beſt <hi>Morality.</hi> The <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> muſt always go together. The <hi>Creed</hi> and the <hi>Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> muſt never, upon any Terms, be parted. The Firſt Part will not do without the Second: 'Tis always defective, and wants the other <hi>Half</hi> to make up a <hi>Whole Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I may therefore boldly ſay, The Subject which I Treat of, is the Beſt I could have choſen. I know no En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment Better for a Chriſtian, than the <hi>Morality</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> which is the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the Style and Method of the following Diſcourſes, I leave them to ſpeak for themſelves. They were the uſual Employment of my Morning-Thoughts, intended chiefly for my own Private Improvement: And, tho' I am far from Admiring
<pb facs="tcp:36225:3"/>them, yet, having found ſome bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit in the Writing, I do not quite deſpair, but that ſome few may find the like in Reading them.</p>
            <p>My Friends, perhaps, may won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to ſee me again in Print; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially after having Publickly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd, That I had <hi>now done Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling.</hi> But, however, I hope they will not Accuſe me of Inconſtancy, when I aſſure them, that my <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and my <hi>Inclination</hi> are ſtill the ſame; and that 'tis only by <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice</hi> that I have chang'd my Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution. They may alſo pleaſe to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect, that having taken ſome pains to prove (in Doubtful Caſes) the Security of <hi>Blind Obedience,</hi> it would look a little ſtrangely if I durſt not venture to Practiſe it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:36225:4"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Diſcourſe I. <hi>Of Hearing the Word of God.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Diſcourſe II. <hi>Of the Advantages of Chriſtianity, and Duties of a Chriſtian.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Diſcourſe III. <hi>Of the Love of God and the World.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Diſcourſe IV. <hi>Of Worldly Policy, and Chriſtian Prudence.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Diſcourſe V. <hi>Of Chriſtian Humility.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Diſcourſe VI. <hi>Of Chriſtian Marriage, and the Means to Sanctifie it.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Diſcourſe VII. <hi>Of True Repentance.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Diſcourſe VIII. <hi>Of the ſmall Number of the Elect.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="discourse">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:36225:4"/>
            <head>Diſcourſe I. Of Hearing the Word of God.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>WHEN many People were gathered together, and made haſte out of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to come to</hi> Jeſus, <hi>he ſpoke by a Parable: The Sower went out to Sow his Seed; and as he Sowed, ſome fell by the way, and it was trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den down, and the Fowls of the Air devour'd it. And ſome fell upon a Rock, and being ſprung up, it wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd away, becauſe it wanted Moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture. And ſome fell among Thorns, and the Thorns ſpringing up with it, choked it. And the other fell upon good Ground, and being ſprung up, bore Fruit an Hundred-fold. And when he had ſaid theſe things, he cried, He that has Ears to hear,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36225:5"/>let him hear. Whereupon his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples ask'd him, What this Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble might be? And he ſaid, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto you it is given to know the Myſtery of the Kingdom of God, but to others in Parables; that Seeing they may not See, and Hearing they may not <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand. Now the Parable is this: The Seed is the Word of God. Thoſe</hi> whoſe Seed falls <hi>by the Way, are they that Hear; and then comes the Devil, and takes the Word out of their Hearts, leſt they ſhould Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and be Saved. They</hi> whoſe Seed falls <hi>upon the Rock, are they who when they have Heard, Receive the Word with Joy; and theſe have no Root: Who for a time Believe, and in time of Temptation fall away. And that which fell among Thorns, are they who have Heard, and going forth are choked with Cares, and Riches, and Pleaſures of this Life, and bring no Fruit. But that <hi>which falls</hi> on the good Ground, are they who in a good and honeſt Heart, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Heard the Word, Keep it, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:36225:5"/>bring forth Fruit with Patience.</hi> Luk. 8. ver. 4, to 16.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God</hi> is the <hi>Seed</hi> of Salvation; the <hi>Seed</hi> of thoſe Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, by which we ſave our Souls. The <hi>Heart</hi> of <hi>Man</hi> is the <hi>Ground</hi> in which this <hi>Seed</hi> is <hi>Sown:</hi> And if the <hi>Ground</hi> be <hi>good,</hi> it will <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive</hi> the <hi>Seed,</hi> and <hi>Keep it,</hi> and <hi>bring forth Fruit with Patience.</hi> 'Tis no wonder therefore, that the Prophet exhorts us to <hi>prepare our Hearts to God, and Serve him only;</hi> becauſe we cannot <hi>Serve him,</hi> unleſs we firſt <hi>prepare our Hearts,</hi> and fit them for his <hi>Service.</hi> It is not Grace alone that makes the difference 'twixt Saints and Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. The very ſame Degree of Grace which is Receiv'd by ſome, is many times Refus'd by others: And the <hi>Receiving</hi> or <hi>Refuſing</hi> of it, very much depends upon the <hi>preparation of our Hearts.</hi> The <hi>Seed</hi> miſcarried Three ſeveral ways: 'Twas <hi>Devour'd, Wither'd</hi> and <hi>Chok'd.</hi> Not becauſe there
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:36225:6"/>were Three forts of Seed, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſame Seed <hi>Fell</hi> upon Three ſorts of <hi>Ground:</hi> The Firſt did not <hi>Receive</hi> it, the Second did not <hi>Keep</hi> it, the Third <hi>brought no Fruit</hi> to perfection.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>The Firſt Ground did not <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive</hi> it: Becauſe 'twas totally Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, and continually Trampled under Foot. The Husbandmen were Idle, and never offer'd to Cultivate it: The Paſſengers were ever buſie, to and fro, and made it too hard for any Seed to Enter. And this is the common Caſe of many People's <hi>Hearts:</hi> 1. They take no Care to <hi>Prepare</hi> them: 2. They ſpare no Pains to <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> them.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They take no Care to <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare their Hearts</hi> for the Recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Word of God.</hi> They never make it any Conſiderable part of their Buſineſs, to be well acquainted with it. If they <hi>read</hi> it, or <hi>hear</hi> it, 'tis either Curioſity
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:36225:6"/>or Cuſtom, 'tis not Inclination, that prompts them to it: And, when all is done, they ſeldom or never ſeriouſly <hi>Conſider</hi> it. For want of a free acquaintance with it, they never know how lovely it is in it ſelf: And for want of loving it, as it deſerves, they give it a very cold reception in their Minds, and none at all in their Hearts. The <hi>Word of God</hi> is in their Ears, when they hear it; in their Minds, when they think of it; but never is in their Hearts, till they Love it. Hatred indeed belongs to the Heart, as well as Love: But Hatred ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhes and drives it away; 'tis only <hi>Love</hi> receives it, and embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces it. And how ſhould they Love it, without knowing the Value of it? Or how ſhould they rightly Underſtand it, without Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing freely and familiarly with it?</p>
               <p>As partial as we are in favour of our ſelves, we cannot reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably expect that our Salvation ſhould coſt us nothing; and that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36225:7"/>God ſhould either force our Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs upon us, whether we will or no, or let us find it by chance, without enquiring after it. 'Tis enough that he is always ready to help us; and that, becauſe he takes delight in Crowning and Rewarding our Labors, therefore he will always have us take ſome pains to help our ſelves. He bids us <hi>ſeek:</hi> He tells us, we <hi>ſhall find:</hi> And, if we do not think the <hi>find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> worth our <hi>ſeeking,</hi> whoſe fault is it but our own? Such Sinners as we are, have little reaſon to complain, that God deals hardly with us, becauſe he does not ſpeak more plainly to us. 'Tis true, our Knowledge of Heavenly things is ſo Myſterious and Obſcure, that St. <hi>Peter</hi> Compares it to a <hi>Light that ſhines in a Dark place:</hi> But however, the leaſt Degree of Knowledge is more than is due to thoſe who deſerve Eternal Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: And beſides, 'tis better for us that it ſhould be ſo. Obſcuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is an Advantage to the Good.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36225:7"/>It Exerciſes their <hi>Faith;</hi> Encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes their hearty Deſires of <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more and more</hi> in this World; and Enflames their fervent Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, for the Happineſs of <hi>Seeing All</hi> in the next. 'Tis then that we are truly Happy, when all the Deſires of our Heart are fully and ſecurely Satisfied: And ſince our Hearts expect to be ſo well Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded there, it is but <hi>juſt</hi> they ſhould be put upon their Trial, and do ſomething to deſerve it here. The Obſcurity of our Faith is the great <hi>Trial</hi> of our <hi>Hearts.</hi> If God had pleas'd to let ſo ſtrong a Light break in upon our Minds, as might Convince us evidently, and force us to <hi>See clearly</hi> what now we only <hi>Believe,</hi> our Heart would have loſt its Liberty of Chuſing, and could not have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd any Thanks for taking the right ſide. The <hi>worſt</hi> of Hearts, as well as the <hi>beſt,</hi> would have equally ſubmitted to the Conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Power of Evidence: And,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:36225:8"/>tho' God's <hi>Mercy</hi> might, perhaps, appear, his <hi>Juſtice</hi> could not ſhew it ſelf, either in puniſhing Sinners, or in the more delightful part of it, the <hi>juſt</hi> Rewarding of Saints: Whereas, according to the preſent Courſe of Providence, his <hi>Juſtice</hi> is as glorious as his <hi>Mercy.</hi> He <hi>Mercifully</hi> gives us <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Strength</hi> ſufficient to <hi>See</hi> and <hi>Do</hi> what he Commands: He Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciles our Liberty with his Decrees: He ſets before us <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Evil,</hi> and puts it in our own free Power to make what Choice we pleaſe. All this is infinitely <hi>Merciful,</hi> and more than we deſerve. His <hi>Light</hi> is always ready to Direct our Steps: There's nothing wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on our part, but that we O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen our Eyes to ſee it. <hi>A good and honeſt Heart</hi> is always willing and prepar'd to <hi>See</hi> and <hi>Do</hi> its Duty. But a Perverſe and Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed One, that frowardly and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Refuſes to <hi>See</hi> its Duty, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it has no mind to <hi>Do</hi> it:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:36225:8"/>A <hi>Heart</hi> that will not apply the <hi>Mind</hi> to an impartial and ſincere conſideration of its Choice, but blindly follows where its inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion leads: A <hi>Heart,</hi> I ſay, which thus Neglects and Slights God's <hi>Mercy,</hi> very well deſerves to fall into the Hands of his Severeſt <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,</hi> and be given over to the Power of <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> which it is ſo fond of.</p>
               <p>We read in the Goſpel, That <hi>when many People were gather'd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and made haſte out of the Cities to come to</hi> Jeſus, <hi>he ſpoke to them by a Parable.</hi> The Eternal <hi>Word</hi> is <hi>made Fleſh:</hi> His <hi>Doctrine</hi> is deliver'd in <hi>Parables:</hi> The one and the other are both of them partly <hi>Manifeſted</hi> to us, and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Hidden</hi> from us; not that they may not be <hi>found</hi> by us, but that we may <hi>ſeek</hi> for a more perfect Knowledge of them, and ſeeking it, we may deſerve to find it. We read, moreover, That <hi>when he had ſaid theſe things, he cried, He
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:36225:9"/>that has Ears to Hear, let him Hear:</hi> That is, He that <hi>Hears,</hi> let him take Care to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand.</hi> They had all of them <hi>Ears to Hear:</hi> But alas! it is not ſufficient to <hi>Hear</hi> with our <hi>Ears;</hi> our Minds and Hearts muſt be Attentive to what we hear, or elſe we hear in vain. <hi>Whereupon his Diſciples as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked him, What this Parable might be? And he ſaid, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto you it is given to know the Myſtery of the Kingdom of God, but to others in Parables.</hi> The reaſon was, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe altho' theſe <hi>others</hi> had Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity enough to <hi>gather together, and make haſte out of the Cities to</hi> See and Hear him, yet when they had Seen and Heard him, they were ſo Unconcern'd and Careleſs, that <hi>Seeing</hi> they did not care to <hi>See,</hi> and <hi>Hearing</hi> they did not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand.</hi> But the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples were more hearty and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, and therefore <hi>unto them it</hi> was <hi>given to know the Myſtery of the Kingdom of God.</hi> The <hi>Parable</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:36225:9"/>gave them ſome little Light. This <hi>little</hi> excited a great deſire of <hi>more.</hi> They <hi>ſought</hi> for it, and they <hi>found</hi> it: They <hi>ask'd</hi> for it, and they <hi>had</hi> it for asking.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It commonly happens, that they who take no Care for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of the <hi>Word of God,</hi> are otherwiſe very buſie, and ſpare no pains to <hi>Harden</hi> their <hi>Hearts</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. A Heart that lyes in common, open to all that comes or goes, a conſtant thorough-fare of idle, vain, impertinent Amuſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, is hardned like the beaten Road, the beſt Counſels make lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or no Impreſſion upon it, 'tis inſenſible of the ſharpeſt Reproof, and impenetrable to all good Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. Whatever <hi>Seed</hi> falls there, it takes no Root; but is imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately <hi>Trodden down,</hi> or preſently <hi>devour'd.</hi> We read in the Goſpel, That when they <hi>hear the Word, the Devil comes, and takes the Word out of their Hearts.</hi> He leaves it in their <hi>Minds;</hi> but at the ſame
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:36225:10"/>time fills their Heads with Crowds of other Thoughts, which Tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple it under Foot, and make their <hi>Hearts</hi> too hard to receive it. He leaves it in their <hi>Minds,</hi> not to Direct them, but to Self-condemn them; and <hi>takes it out of their Hearts,</hi> for fear <hi>leſt they ſhould Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and be Saved.</hi> He fears they would love it, if they began to like it: He fears they would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it firmly, and hold faſt to it, if they loved it: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is afraid they would be <hi>Saved,</hi> if they <hi>Believ'd</hi> it. For this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, he is ever buſie in contriving Ways and Means to Secure their <hi>Hearts</hi> to himſelf. He manages all manner of Temptations with his utmoſt Skill, to enſlave them to the Pleaſures of this Life: He never fails, in time and ſeaſon, to Suggeſt ſuch Thoughts as he ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines may Create a Prejudice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Duty, and the Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties of it: He puſhes them on from one Folly to another, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:36225:10"/>drives them into a perpetual Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of Diverſions and Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which leave no room for Reading, Meditating, Praying, and Endeavouring to Save their Souls: And thus, at length, he Corrupts them to ſuch a Degree, that they cannot endure to Hear the <hi>Word of God,</hi> becauſe they cannot abide to <hi>Believe</hi> it. They are ſo far from caring for the Light of Faith, that they take all Care imaginable to avoid it. They deſpiſe and hate it, becauſe it only Diſcovers to them a <hi>Heaven,</hi> which they do not Reliſh, and Diſturbs them with unwelcome Thoughts of a <hi>Hell,</hi> which makes them Tremble. Their <hi>Hearts</hi> are wilfully <hi>Blind,</hi> and obſtinately <hi>Deaf:</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>they ſeeing, ſee not; and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, hear not.</hi> Our Saviour thus deſcribes them in the Thirteenth of S. <hi>Matthew; Their Heart is groſs, their Ears are dull of hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and they ſhut their Eyes,</hi> for fear <hi>leſt at any time they ſhould See,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:36225:11"/>and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand with their Heart, and ſhould be Converted, and I ſhould Heal them.</hi> They are not ſo much afraid of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> with their <hi>Mind;</hi> becauſe the <hi>Mind</hi> only <hi>Preaches,</hi> 'tis the <hi>Heart</hi> that <hi>Practiſes.</hi> Their great fear is, <hi>leſt at any time they ſhould <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand with their Heart.</hi> They have not patience to think of any real and effectual Change of Life; and therefore are afraid of changing their <hi>Fooliſh Hearts,</hi> and bringing them to a better <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> of the <hi>Word of God, leſt at any time they</hi> ſhould begin to <hi>Love</hi> it, take <hi>Delight</hi> in it, and <hi>Practiſe</hi> it. The Devil is always watchful to <hi>take the Word out of their Hearts:</hi> And they are no leſs Careful to keep it always out. He <hi>takes</hi> it <hi>out,</hi> for fear <hi>leſt they ſhould Believe and be Saved:</hi> They keep it out, for the ſame reaſon, <hi>leſt at any time they ſhould be Converted and Heal'd.</hi> The Devil fears nothing more, than that they ſhould <hi>Believe</hi> it,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:36225:11"/>
                  <hi>ſo</hi> as to be <hi>Saved:</hi> And they are ſo much of his Mind, ſo fully in his Power, and ſo <hi>led Captive by</hi> him <hi>at his pleaſure,</hi> that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil himſelf is not more afraid of it than they are.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>When the Heart of Man is thus doubly hardned, from without, and from within, 'tis no great wonder, that it does not <hi>receive</hi> the <hi>Word of God.</hi> No wonder, I ſay, that the <hi>Seed,</hi> which falls <hi>by the way, is trodden down,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently <hi>devour'd.</hi> But the Second ſort of Ground is ſomething bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than the Firſt. Though it be <hi>Stony</hi> underneath, yet it is cover'd over with ſome little Earth, which readily <hi>receives</hi> the <hi>Seed,</hi> and helps it to <hi>ſpring up,</hi> although it does not <hi>keep</hi> it, nor allow it any <hi>Root.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>S. <hi>Luke</hi> ſays, <hi>It wither'd away, becauſe it wanted Moiſture.</hi> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed there are ſome certain Tears of hearty and ſincere Repentance,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:36225:12"/>which are apt to mollifie the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Heart, and ſoften all the <hi>Stony places</hi> in it. They are, as it were, the Dew of Heaven, that Heavenly <hi>Moiſture</hi> which Nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes the <hi>Love of God,</hi> and of his Holy <hi>Word,</hi> and helping the <hi>Seed</hi> to Enter <hi>Deeply,</hi> hinders it from being <hi>Scorch'd</hi> and <hi>Wither'd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Thirteenth of S. <hi>Matthew</hi> we read, that the <hi>Seed which fell upon ſtony places, ſprung up imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, becauſe it had no deepneſs of Earth;</hi> and preſently <hi>Wither'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, becauſe it had no Root.</hi> It was ſoon up, for want of <hi>Depth;</hi> and ſoon down, for want of <hi>Root.</hi> The Love of this World, in the Heart of many Chriſtians, who prefer it before God, and do not know they do ſo, is like a <hi>Rock</hi> under Ground. The Soil ſeems good; and, ſo much as there is, it really is ſo; but becauſe there is no more of it, 'tis little better than none at all. It is not <hi>Deep</hi> enough to be fruitful. The <hi>Seed</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:36225:12"/>immediately Enters; but being little Cover'd, and leſs <hi>Rooted,</hi> is preſently <hi>Wither'd</hi> with the firſt heat that <hi>Scorches</hi> it.</p>
               <p>The generality of Mankind are ſtrangely in love with this fooliſh World, and violently fond of tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory things, belonging to this preſent Life. Their Worldly Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Wealth, and Pleaſure, are dearer to them, than their Lives; and this Life dearer to them, than the next. When they hear of the next, and are awaken'd with a lively Apprehenſion of a future State, where Everlaſting Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs attends them, if they pleaſe; they <hi>receive the Word with joy,</hi> and are very glad to underſtand that, when they have done being <hi>Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py</hi> here, they may, perhaps, begin to be <hi>ſo</hi> there. They are not very much Charm'd with what they hear of Heaven; they know not how to reliſh thoſe Spiritual Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, which are too refin'd for Senſual and Carnal Souls; but
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:36225:13"/>however, they preſume, that God, who cannot but be infinitely Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in himſelf, muſt needs know how to make them Happy when he takes them to him; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when their own Felicity is ſpent, which they deſire may laſt as long as poſſible, they then are willing to try what Heaven is, and ſee if it can make amends for what they leave behind them. Upon theſe Terms, they ſeem to love God pretty well; but 'tis too plain, they love themſelves a great deal better. And the more we conſider the matter, the plainer 'twill appear, that it is not ſo much the <hi>Love</hi> of God which <hi>Leads</hi> them, as it is the <hi>Fear</hi> of Hell which <hi>Drives</hi> them, into a Deſire of Heaven.</p>
               <p>Fear is a troubleſome Paſſion: And Hell is a thing ſo terrible, that even thoſe who have no mind to believe it, are not eaſie in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, when they admit a ſerious thought of it. It ſoures all World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:36225:13"/>Comforts, and Embitters the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments of this Life. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for their own dear ſakes, that they may Love the World Securely, and Enjoy it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with an undiſturb'd and quiet Mind, they are willing to come to a Compoſition, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with all the Exterior Duties of Religion, provided they may keep their Heart to themſelves, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow it where they pleaſe, without being oblig'd to Wean it from the World, and Diſengage it from the Treacherous Endearments of it. For this reaſon they are very exact in all their Pariſh-Devotions, punctual in their times of Morning and Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Prayer, diligent in Hearing Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, chearful in giving Alms, and charitable in comforting the Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. All this they are ready to do, and any thing elſe, whatever it is, that does not hinder them from lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and enjoying Themſelves, the World, and their own Humour, as much as ever. And all this they are the more willing to do, becauſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:36225:14"/>it pacifies the troubleſom Remorſes of their Conſcience; it cheats them into a belief that they are better than they are; it makes them hope they love God better than they do; and that they are not ſo very fond of any Worldly Satisfactions, as not to leave them all for God's ſake, when occaſion requires.</p>
               <p>The out-ſide of their Piety Amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes them, but the in-ſide of their Heart is always Hidden from them. They take no Pains to Search the Bottom of it, and to diſcover the wretched Corruption of their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plac'd Affections; becauſe there are ſome certain things in which they are fully determin'd never to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe any Self-denial; they will not hear of any reaſon to the contrary; but in ſpite of all the Reaſon in the World, they are reſolved upon the Point, that ſuch things <hi>muſt</hi> and <hi>ſhall</hi> be reaſonable, becauſe they have a mind they ſhould be ſo. In o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matters, where their ſtrongeſt Paſſions are not much concern'd,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:36225:14"/>they can comply with eaſe. They can Read, and Pray, and <hi>Hear the Word of God with Joy;</hi> they can Conceive ſome good Deſires; they can be very much pleas'd with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſenſible Devotion for the preſent: But when theſe Pious thoughts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to ſink a little deeper in their Hearts, and to contrive a real and effectual Reformation of their Lives; when the <hi>Seed</hi> begins to take <hi>Root:</hi> 'Tis then it meets with great and unexpected Reſiſtance, and finds under a tender Surface, nothing but the hardneſs of a <hi>Rock.</hi> Their World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Honour, their Eſtate, their Eaſe, are things which muſt not, upon any Terms, be call'd in queſtion. They are <hi>hardned</hi> in a Selfiſh, Proud, and Sullen Reſolution, of never parting with them: And, till the time of Trial comes, they do not know how <hi>hard</hi> their Obſtinacy is. When all goes proſperouſly on, and Danger looks upon them at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, almoſt out of ſight, they then can make a ſhift, in a kind fit,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:36225:15"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:36225:15"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:36225:16"/>to offer all theſe things to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, and addreſs his Infinite Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty with the uſual Complement, of being ready, upon all Occaſions, to ſtand by him with their Lives and Fortunes. But notwithſtanding all this, the Goſpel aſſures us, that theſe dutiful Expreſſions of their <hi>Mind</hi> have <hi>no Root</hi> in their <hi>Heart:</hi> Theſe Loyaliſts <hi>endure but for a time:</hi> And <hi>afterward, when</hi> any <hi>Perſecution or Affliction ariſes,</hi> they find, <hi>in time</hi> of <hi>Temptation,</hi> how much they were miſtaken in themſelves; <hi>immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they fall away.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>The third ſort of Ground <hi>receives</hi> the <hi>Seed,</hi> and <hi>keeps</hi> it. It keeps it warm and deep, and helps it to take <hi>Root.</hi> But becauſe the <hi>Thorns</hi> take deeper Root, ſpread farther, and riſe higher, therefore the <hi>Seed</hi> is <hi>choked,</hi> and <hi>brings no Fruit.</hi> Theſe <hi>Thorns,</hi> according to the Goſpel, are the <hi>Cares of this Life.</hi> As for the <hi>Life to come,</hi> we cannot be too
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:36225:16"/>
                  <hi>Careful</hi> of it; we cannot love God too much; we cannot have too great a Paſſion for the Joys of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. But as for this poor Earth, this Dirt, which only fouls and cloggs our Feet, this Clay, in which we often ſtick ſo faſt, alaſs! this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable World has nothing in it that deſerves our <hi>Care,</hi> except it be get well out of it, and make it a ſafe Paſſage to a better. Whatever may be uſeful to this End, we may be careful of it. But as for any thing elſe, belonging to this wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Life, the Goſpel gives us warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to avoid the Danger of ſuch Needleſs and Pernicious <hi>Cares,</hi> which hinder the <hi>Word of God</hi> from being <hi>fruitful</hi> in our <hi>Hearts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Danger is the greater, becauſe theſe <hi>Cares</hi> are of an earlier Growth; the Roots of them come into the World with us: They take Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Hearts, for ſeveral Years, before the uſe of Reaſon has prepar'd us for the <hi>Word of God.</hi> We read, that the <hi>Seed fell among Thorns;</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:36225:17"/>which plainly ſuppoſes, that the <hi>Thorns</hi> were firſt Poſſeſſors of the <hi>Ground.</hi> But yet, if they had been extirpated before the <hi>Seed</hi> was <hi>ſown,</hi> it might have <hi>ſprung up</hi> ſafely by it ſelf, there would have been no <hi>Thorns</hi> to <hi>ſpring up with it,</hi> and <hi>choke it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Thorns</hi> have great Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage over the <hi>Seed.</hi> Not only their Growth is earlier, but quicker, and more natural. The Corruption of our Heart is like the Rankneſs of a Soil, to which they eaſily take, and where they thrive at a ſtrange rate. There needs no planting, watering, or taking any Care of them. 'Tis but letting them alone; they grow apace, and ſpring up of themſelves. But it is not ſo with Piety and Vertue. There muſt be Sowing, Planting, Cultivating: No Pains muſt be ſpared to keep them in good order; and all that we can do is little enough to make them <hi>bring forth Fruit,</hi> altho' there were no <hi>Thorns</hi> to hinder them.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:36225:17"/>
               <p>I tremble when I think how ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true this is. Experience teaches it; the Goſpel it ſelf confirms it; and our Conſcience cannot deny it. We daily ſee how careful moſt Men are of <hi>this</hi> World, and how careleſs of the <hi>next.</hi> They lay up <hi>Riches,</hi> and provide for <hi>Pleaſures.</hi> Theſe are their principal <hi>Cares,</hi> which our Saviour mentions in the Goſpel. They are very highly concern'd for living long, with all their Plenty and their Eaſe about them: But as for living well, and laying in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for a happy Eternity; they entertain theſe Thoughts with Cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Indifference. The leaſt Proſpect of Danger, attending their Worldly <hi>Riches,</hi> or their <hi>Pleaſures,</hi> is enough to break their Sleep. The very Apprehenſion of a Momenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Poverty or Miſery, tho' at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, is enough to put their Minds upon the Rack, and torture the very Souls of them: But as for Eternal <hi>Riches,</hi> and Heavenly <hi>Pleaſures,</hi> tho' theſe are perhaps in greater Danger,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:36225:18"/>they can ſleep ſecurely: All the Cruel Poverty and Everlaſting Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Hell it ſelf, tho' they are loud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly threatned with its being nearer than they are aware of, all this will not Rouze them, and Awaken them into a true Senſe of their Duty. So Stupid and Inſenſible our Nature is in all things, which regard the other World, and yet ſo Vigorous, ſo Active, and ſo Buſie in the <hi>Cares</hi> of this.</p>
               <p>The Conſequence is natural and plain. There's no Excuſe can be admitted in the Caſe. We muſt conſider, on the one Hand, the Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and on the other, the Folly of theſe <hi>Worldly Cares:</hi> We muſt go to work with both our Hands, and labour with all our Strength, to pull them up by the Roots. Without this, all our other Labours are in vain. We may Confeſs our Sins; we may be Sorry for them; we may purpoſe to Amend: But all theſe Pious Endeavours will be fruitleſs, and without effect; we
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:36225:18"/>ſhall immediately relapſe again; our Sorrow and our Purpoſes will never be Victorious, whilſt our Worldly Cares are ſtronger, and more preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent. We muſt therefore lay this Matter ſeriouſly to Heart. Eternity depends upon it. The more we conſider it, the more we ſhall be ſenſible of the Importance of it. 'Tis a common thing to meet with Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who wonder ſtrangely at their own Frailty, and cannot, without Horror and Amazement, reflect how long they have continued in a Sinful Courſe; in ſpite of all the Pains which they have often taken to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend their Lives. But yet, for my part, I can never wonder that Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple loſe their Labour, when they go the wrong way to work. If they will not take Advice, when God himſelf is pleas'd to give it them, I know not how to help it. He tells them plainly, that whilſt they ſow <hi>among Thorns,</hi> the <hi>Seed</hi> will never <hi>bring forth Fruit.</hi> And this is a fair Warning to them, to begin the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:36225:19"/>of their Lives, by labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all they can, to root out all theſe <hi>Thorns,</hi> all Worldly Paſſions and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections whatſoever, from whence thoſe <hi>Cares</hi> ariſe, which <hi>choke</hi> the <hi>Seed,</hi> obſtruct the <hi>Word of God,</hi> and hinder it from being Fruitful in their Hearts.</p>
               <p>I do not deſcend to Particulars, becauſe the Caſe is general, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt Exception. No Love of any Creature whatſoever muſt ever dare to ſtand in Competition with the Love of our Creator. All o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Loves muſt be reſign'd and moderate; ſubmiſſive to God's Holy Will, contented with his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments, always Calm, Serene, and Undiſturb'd. When <hi>Worldly Cares</hi> are thus reſtrain'd, they are no more than <hi>Duties:</hi> But when they paſs theſe Limits, then it is that they are <hi>Thorns;</hi> which not only prick our Feet, but pierce the very Hearts of us: They wound our Feet, I mean thoſe Pious Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of our Soul, which are the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:36225:19"/>only Feet by which we move to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Heaven, and pierce our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience with a terrible Remorſe of loving <hi>this</hi> World too much, and for ought we know, a great deal more than the <hi>next.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis poſſible, you'll ſay, to love the World to a very great degree, and yet love God a little better; which if we do, we love him above all things, and that's enough to ſave us. But ſurely you are not in good earneſt. Your <hi>whole</hi> Heart is due to him: And can you think you do him Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, by allowing him a <hi>little more</hi> than <hi>half?</hi> Your <hi>whole</hi> Heart ought to be a <hi>Houſe of Prayer:</hi> And is it juſt, to make <hi>almoſt</hi> one <hi>half</hi> of it a <hi>Den of Thieves?</hi> Your <hi>whole</hi> Heart ought to be the <hi>Temple of God:</hi> And dare you offer to <hi>defile</hi> it, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a Partition in it, and erecting Altars to his Mortal Enemies, the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil?</p>
               <p>A true Chriſtian cannot be ſo falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted. If we believe the Goſpel, He has the <hi>beſt</hi> of Hearts: His <hi>Heart</hi>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:36225:20"/>is <hi>Good and Honeſt:</hi> He's no Trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer betwixt God and the World: He hates all double Dealing, and endeavouring to pleaſe both Parties: He ſcorns to do ſo mean and baſe a thing, as to divide His Heart, and ſteal away any part of it from him who has a Right to All. He does not <hi>uſe the World,</hi> becauſe He <hi>loves</hi> it, but becauſe He <hi>needs</hi> it. He Eats, and Drinks, and Sleeps, that He may live: He does not live, that He may Eat, and Drink, and Sleep. If He takes care of His good Name, it is becauſe it will enable Him to do more Good. If He di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts himſelf, 'tis only to refreſh His Spirits, and prepare them for a better uſe. He knows very well, that all the Comforts and Reliefs of our Corrupted, Weak, and Sickly Nature, are very pleaſing and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful to it, and are therefore apt to entice our Hearts to love them. But alas! He ſees, and grieves at his diſeaſed Condition: And, tho' He gladly <hi>uſes</hi> the <hi>Remedies,</hi> becauſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:36225:20"/>His Nature wants them, and His Miſery makes it His Duty to apply them; yet He is ſo far from <hi>loving</hi> them, that He could wiſh with all His Heart, He were ſo Healthy and ſo Happy, as not to ſtand in need of them. The Sores of His Morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity are grievous to Him, and the itching Pleaſure of His Plaiſters does not make him ſuch Amends, but that He had much rather be without them. He hears, and He believes, there is a State of Immortality, where Health and Happineſs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect Him; where He may be ſure to find them; if He pleaſe; and where, once found, it is impoſſible to loſe them. The <hi>Word of God</hi> aſſures him of it. And this is the <hi>Word,</hi> which, <hi>in a good and honeſt Heart,</hi> he <hi>receives</hi> joyfully, <hi>keeps</hi> faithfully, and <hi>brings forth Fruit, with Patience,</hi> becauſe he is not ſo much concern'd for any Worldly Matter, as to be <hi>impatient</hi> about it.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="discourse">
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:36225:21"/>
            <head>Diſcourſe II. Of the Advantages of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, and Duties of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>JEſus ſaid to his Diſciples, Bleſſed are the Eyes which ſee the things that you ſee. For I tell you, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Prophets and Kings have deſired to ſee thoſe things which you ſee, and have not ſeen them; and to hear thoſe things which you hear, and have not heard them. And behold a certain Lawyer ſtood up, and tempted him, ſaying, What ſhall I do to poſſeſs E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Life? He ſaid unto him, What is written in the Law? How readeſt thou? And he anſwering, ſaid, Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy Heart, and with all thy Soul, and with all thy Strength, and with all thy Mind, and thy Neighbour as thy ſelf. And he ſaid unto him, Thou haſt anſwered right; this do,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:36225:21"/>and thou ſhalt live. But he willing to juſtifie himſelf, ſaid unto Jeſus, And who is my Neighbour? And Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus anſwering, ſaid, A certain Man went down from</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>to</hi> Jeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho, <hi>and fell among Robbers, who ſtript him, and wounded him, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, leaving him half dead. And by chance there came down a certain Prieſt that way, and when he ſaw him, he paſſed by. And likewiſe a</hi> Levite, <hi>when he was at the place, came, and looked on him, and paſſed by. But a certain</hi> Samaritan, <hi>as he travelled, came where he was; and when he ſaw him, he had Compaſſion on him, and went to him, and bound up his Wounds, pouring in Oil and Wine, and ſet him on his own Beaſt, and brought him to an Inn, and took care of him. And on the Morrow he took out Two Pence, and gave them to the Hoſt, and ſaid unto him, Take Care of him; and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever thou ſpendeſt more, when I come again, I will repay thee. Which now of theſe three, thinkeſt thou, was Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour unto him that fell among the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:36225:22"/>Robbers? And he ſaid, he that ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Mercy unto him. Then ſaid Jeſus unto him, Go, and do thou likewiſe.</hi> Luke 10. v. 23, to 38.</p>
            <p>The Glorious Advantages of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, and the Principal Duties of a Chriſtian, are the whole Matter of this Goſpel. The <hi>Advantages</hi> are ſo great, that we ſhould be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful, if we paſs'd them ſlightly over; and the <hi>Duties</hi> are of ſuch Importance, that we ſhould be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſeable, if we refus'd to take them into ſerious Coſideration.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>S. <hi>Paul,</hi> in his Second Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> conſiders the Prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minency of the Law of <hi>Chriſt</hi> above the Law of <hi>Moſes:</hi> And, that we may better underſtand the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, it will not be amiſs to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Riſe and Progreſs of the Divine Law, from the firſt Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of it. God in the firſt Creation gave to Man a Natural Knowledge of his Duty; which
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:36225:22"/>Knowledge is the Law of Nature. By this, <hi>Abel</hi> offer'd Sacrifice, <hi>Enoch</hi> walkt with God, <hi>Abraham</hi> paid Tythes to <hi>Melchiſedec, Lot</hi> was ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitable to Strangers, <hi>Job</hi> was Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, Juſt, and Humble. In a Word, All the Saints, who lived before the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> by the Light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, were inſtructed in their Duty. Mean time, the growing Malice of Corrupted Nature every Day encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; the Will became more prone to Evil; and the Cuſtom of tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, being, as it were, a ſecond Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſuperinduced a ſecond Law, which the Apoſtle calls the <hi>Law of Sin.</hi> The Dictates of this <hi>Law of Sin,</hi> altho' they were not able to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face the Original Impreſſion of the Law of God, yet they obſcured and darkned it: The Underſtanding, which ought to have led the Will, was now miſled and blinded by it: And. Vice prevailing almoſt univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally, the Law of God was, in a manner, out of Sight, and out of Mind. When the World was in
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:36225:23"/>this deſperate Condition, God, of his Infinite Mercy, promulgated the Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> the Morality of which was formerly well known, tho' now neglected, and almoſt quite forgotten. Then it was that <hi>the Law was written in their Tables,</hi> ſays S. <hi>Auſtin, becauſe they did not read it in their Hearts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The manner of its Delivery is very remarkable. <hi>When the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of</hi> Iſrael <hi>were gone out of the Land of</hi> Egypt, <hi>they came into the Wilderneſs of</hi> Sinai, <hi>and Camp'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Mount;</hi> where the Ten Commandments were proclaim'd with Thunder and Lightning; the Earth quaking, and the People trembling at what they ſaw and heard. The Morality of theſe Commandments was neither more nor leſs than the Law of Nature; which, as promulgated by <hi>Moſes,</hi> is called the <hi>Old Law;</hi> and, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> is call'd the <hi>New.</hi> Not that the Law it ſelf, as to the Moral Part of it, is different
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:36225:23"/>from what it was; but that the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, I mean the Motives and Advantages are <hi>New,</hi> and infinitely ſurpaſſing thoſe of the <hi>Old.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the <hi>New Law,</hi> the Motives which induce us to obſerve it, are incomparably greater. The <hi>Jews</hi> generally fear'd nothing but Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Puniſhments; they hoped for nothing but Temporal Rewards; their Self-love aim'd at nothing more than Earthly Happineſs; and even God himſelf, who knew their Hearts were harder than the Stones, on which he Engrav'd their Law, propos'd no better Motives to them. They were to be Train'd up by De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees to fear and to obey the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of their <hi>Nature,</hi> before they could be well prepared to Entertain the Myſteries of <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Glory.</hi> And thus we read, in the Nineteenth Chapter of <hi>Exodus,</hi> how God Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded <hi>Moſes,</hi> to mind the People of what <hi>he had done to the Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> and that now, having <hi>brought</hi> them <hi>to himſelf,</hi> if they would <hi>obey
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:36225:24"/>his Voice,</hi> he would take them into his particular Care, <hi>above all</hi> other <hi>People;</hi> and, to Encourage them the more, he would have them know, that <hi>All the Earth</hi> was <hi>his.</hi> They were to remember the Plagues of <hi>Egypt,</hi> that they might not forget their Duty, but that their fears might be awaken'd with expecting the like Severity in caſe of Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. And, to maintain their hopes, it was enough that <hi>All the Earth</hi> was <hi>his;</hi> for this was All they wiſh'd for; and therefore, if they Obey'd, he was able to Reward them to the utmoſt of their Hearts deſire. In the Twenty ſixth of <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viticus,</hi> he tells them, <hi>If you keep my Commandments, I will give you Rain in due Seaſon; and the Land ſhall yield her increaſe; you ſhall eat your Bread to the full; you ſhall Chaſe your Enemies, and they ſhall fall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you; and you ſhall dwell in your own Land ſafely.</hi> And in the Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty eighth of <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> he aſſures them, <hi>All theſe Bleſſings ſhall come
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:36225:24"/>upon you, if you will hearken to my Voice:</hi> But <hi>if you will not hearken to it,</hi> Then <hi>All</hi> the contrary <hi>Curſes ſhall</hi> be ſure to <hi>overtake you.</hi> Poor Creatures! And was <hi>This</hi> All! Was <hi>This</hi> the utmoſt proſpect of their Hopes and Fears! Theſe Little, Earthly, and Tranſitory Comforts, are they worthy to compare with that ineſtimable Bleſſing promiſed by our Saviour; <hi>Come ye Bleſſed of my Father,</hi> Come <hi>and poſſeſs the</hi> great and everlaſting <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Heaven, <hi>which was prepared for you from the Foundation of the World?</hi> Or are the <hi>Curſes</hi> which deprive us of theſe Empty and Unſatisfying Pleaſures, are they comparable to that final Curſe of our Redeemer, <hi>Go ye Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed into Everlaſting Fire, which was prepared for the Devil and his Angels?</hi> No, no. The Eternal Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which no Tongue is able to expreſs; the Everlaſting Joys of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, which <hi>never enter'd into the Heart of Man;</hi> and the endearing Charms of God's prodigious Love, by which
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:36225:25"/>he ſent his Son, not only to teach us theſe great Truths, but to Aſſiſt us with his Conquering Grace, and to Redeem us with his Precious Blood: Theſe, theſe I ſay, are new Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages incomparably ſurpaſſing All that the Old Law ever could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, there were many Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Patriarchs, and Kings amongſt them, who were more Enlightned than the reſt; and, tho' they had not <hi>received theſe</hi> glorious <hi>Promiſes,</hi> yet they had ſome fore-knowledge of <hi>them afar off,</hi> and languiſh'd with continual Expectations and Deſires to ſee the Accompliſhment of them. And therefore 'tis no wonder that we find it written, in the beginning of this Goſpel; <hi>Jeſus ſaid to his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples: Bleſſed are the Eyes which ſee the things that you ſee. For I tell you that many Prophets and Kings have deſired to ſee thoſe things which you ſee, and have not ſeen them; and to hear thoſe things which you hear, and have not heard them.</hi> We <hi>ſee</hi> the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:36225:25"/>
                  <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> Eſtabliſh'd firmly and ſecurely; <hi>Bleſſed are the Eyes that ſee it.</hi> We <hi>hear</hi> his <hi>Goſpel</hi> Preach'd, and faithfully Deliver'd to us: <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are the Ears that hear it.</hi> And <hi>Bleſſed</hi> indeed we are, if we not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>hear the Word of God, but</hi> alſo <hi>keep it.</hi> Alas! Theſe great <hi>Advantages</hi> of Chriſtianity will little avail us: They will only ſerve to riſe in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt us, and to heap a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Damnation upon us, if we neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the <hi>Duties</hi> of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>We read in the Goſpel, how <hi>a certain Lawyer ſtood up,</hi> and ask'd our Saviour, <hi>What ſhall I do, to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs Eternal Life?</hi> He thought (and with a great deal of reaſon) that ſo vaſt a Purchaſe, as <hi>Eternal Life,</hi> was never to be had for nothing: He knew that all this Momentary Life of ours, is nothing to <hi>Eternity,</hi> which ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows up all <hi>Time,</hi> with a diſpropor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion infinitely greater than a Drop of Water loſes it ſelf in the Ocean:
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:36225:26"/>And therefore he juſtly ſuſpected, that perhaps his uttermoſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours would fall ſhort of it. <hi>What ſhall I do,</hi> ſays he, <hi>to poſſeſs Eternal Life?</hi> Theſe words of his, expreſs an earneſt and a ſincere deſire, not only to <hi>know</hi> his Duty, but to <hi>do</hi> it: And truly, unleſs we fully and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely reſolve to <hi>do</hi> it, we had bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter never <hi>know</hi> it. Are we as hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily deſirous as he ſeem'd to be? Are we as much in earneſt? Are we as ſincere? If ſo; Hear then <hi>what's written in the Law. Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God, with all thy Heart, and with all thy Soul, and with all thy Strength, and with all thy Mind, and thy Neighbour as thy ſelf.</hi> Conſider this well; and then attend to what our Saviour ſays: <hi>Do this, and you ſhall live: Do</hi> but <hi>this, and you ſhall</hi> certainly <hi>poſſeſs Eternal Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And is it hard to do ſo much as this? He is infinitely lovely in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and is it therefore a difficult thing to love him? He infinitely deſerves our Love, and therefore we
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:36225:26"/>can never Love him ſo much as he deſerves: But muſt we therefore never Love him as much as we can? Let us do our utmoſt, we can never Love him ſo much as he Loves us; and although we had each of us a Thouſand Hearts entirely at his Service, we ſhould never be able to make a ſuitable return: Since there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we have only one, Can we for ſhame refuſe him any part of that? 'Tis All of it due; and can we make abatements? 'Tis all of it too lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and can we think it too much?</p>
               <p>There's only one Objection obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in this Caſe. If we muſt <hi>Love God with all our Heart, with all our Soul, with all our Strength, with all our Mind,</hi> it ſeems to follow, that we muſt Love nothing elſe. Now this is evidently a great Miſtake, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Scripture immediately adds, that we muſt <hi>Love our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as our ſelves;</hi> from whence it follows clearly: 1. That we muſt <hi>Love our ſelves.</hi> 2. That, as we <hi>Love our ſelves,</hi> ſo we muſt <hi>Love
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:36225:27"/>our Neighbour</hi> alſo. 'Tis enough therefore, that <hi>with all our Mind</hi> we <hi>principally</hi> conſider our Duty to our God, <hi>with all our Strength</hi> endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour <hi>chiefly</hi> to Serve him, and <hi>with all our Heart and Soul</hi> Embrace him, as the <hi>moſt</hi> Tranſcending Object of our beſt Affections. 'Tis enough, I ſay, that we never Love any thing elſe, but either by his Order, or with his Leave: And that all our Love, of any Creature whatſoever, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Subordinate to the Love of God, and ready, upon all occaſions, to give place to it, without ever offering to ſtand one Moment in Competition with it. Remember what our Saviour ſays: <hi>Do this, and you ſhall</hi> certainly <hi>poſſeſs Eternal Life.</hi> But at the ſame time, pray remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that, unleſs you <hi>Do this,</hi> you <hi>ſhall</hi> certainly <hi>never poſſeſs</hi> it.</p>
               <p>It ſeems a little ſtrange, that this Lawyer, who was ſo very skilful in the general Doctrine of the Law, was yet ſo ignorant in the particular Application of it. He knew that
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:36225:27"/>all the Precepts of the Law were comprehended in theſe Two, of <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God</hi> above all things, and <hi>our Neighbour</hi> as our ſelves: And yet he knew not who his Neighbour was, but ask'd our Saviour the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <hi>Who is my Neighbour?</hi> Is it a Friend? A Benefactor? A Relation? An Acquaintance? A Partner? A Fellow-Citizen? A Countrey-Man? Or is it generally any Perſon United to us in ſome Common Bond of Humane Society? I am afraid that many Chriſtians are as ignorant as this <hi>Phariſee</hi> was. They generally Love themſelves to that Degree, as not to Care for any Body elſe, but thoſe who are, ſome way or other, Inſtrumental, Uſeful, or Serviceable, to their Honour, Intereſt or Pleaſure. Without ſomething of this, 'tis no great matter what becomes of them. Whether they Sink of Swim, 'tis all the ſame. If this were all that is Commanded by the Second Precept of the Law, this part of the way to Heaven would be Broad enough:
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:36225:28"/>We then ſhould have no need to fear, that <hi>there are few that find it;</hi> we might be aſſured there would be <hi>none</hi> that <hi>miſs</hi> it. To Love our Neighbour for our own ſake, is as eaſie as it is to Love our ſelves: But on the contrary, to Love him pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for God's ſake, is as hard a Task as 'tis to Love our Maker better than our ſelves. If we Love God above all things, and conſequently above our ſelves; this Love, when it extends to our Neighbour, will naturally ſet a greater value upon his Relation to God, than his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion with us. We ſhall not then ſo much conſider his Affinity, his Kindneſs, or his Uſefulneſs; but we ſhall chiefly regard his being made to the ſame Divine Image, Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the ſame Precious Blood, and therefore being capable of the ſame Grace in this World, and the ſame Glory in the next. Let a Man be never ſo much a Stranger to us, nay, let him be our greateſt Enemy, yet it is ſtill true, that his Creation, his
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:36225:28"/>Redemption, his Capacity of Grace and Glory, are the ſame as ours: And therefore, if we Love God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things, and our ſelves in order to him, we are bound to Love our Neighbour principally upon theſe Accounts; that is to ſay, we are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliged to Love him, as we Love our ſelves.</p>
               <p>The truth of this Doctrine is plain and clear in our Saviour's Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of the <hi>Samaritan.</hi> When he ſaw a Naked Man lye Bleeding, and <hi>Half-dead</hi> of his <hi>Wounds,</hi> 'twas enough to move his <hi>Compaſſion,</hi> and to make him overlook all private Conſiderations of his being not only a Stranger, but perhaps an Enemy to him; for the <hi>Jews,</hi> in thoſe Days, had ſuch a Mortal Enmity againſt the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> that they would not endure either to Eat or Drink with them. But not withſtanding all this, He was framed of the ſame Fleſh and Blood, he was made to the Image of the ſame God, he had a Juſt Title to the Common Duties
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:36225:29"/>of Humanity; and therefore the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritan went to him,</hi> he <hi>pour'd Oyl and Wine</hi> into his Wounds, he <hi>bound</hi> them <hi>up,</hi> he <hi>ſet him upon his own</hi> Horſe, he <hi>brought him to an Inn, and took Care on him.</hi> This was not all. When he had brought him thither, another Perſon would perhaps have thought that he had done enough for one Man's ſhare, and would have left him to the mercy of the Inn, where every Body elſe was as much oblig'd, as he, to <hi>have Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion on him.</hi> But the <hi>Samaritan</hi> was not content with doing half his Duty; he was not certain that the People of the Inn were willing to ſupply the reſt; and therefore he not only left Money in the Hands of his Hoſt, but alſo left Orders to let him want for nothing, aſſuring him, that if the Money fell ſhort, whatſoever he laid out more, he would faithfully repay every Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. The <hi>Samaritan,</hi> if he had been ſo Hard, ſo Cruel, and ſo Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſh, as we are, he might have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:36225:29"/>a Thouſand of thoſe cautious pretences which are common in the World: But his Charity was too ſincere, to need any Excuſe; and too great, to allow it.</p>
               <p>Our Saviour not only Preach'd this Doctrine, but alſo Practis'd it. The Parable is not only <hi>His,</hi> but <hi>He</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the principal Perſon repreſented in it. When <hi>Adam</hi> Sinned, he <hi>went down</hi> from Paradiſe into a Vale of Miſeries, where not only He, but his Poſterity, are <hi>ſtript</hi> of all the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal Robes of Innocence, and <hi>fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> into the Hands of their own diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly Paſſions, which are worſe than <hi>Robbers,</hi> by whom they are dangerouſly <hi>Wounded,</hi> and left <hi>Half Dead.</hi> Our Saviour <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the true <hi>Samaritan,</hi> ſaw our Condition, and took Pity on us. He deſcended from Heaven, he pour'd his Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Blood into our Wounds, he Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged himſelf with the Burthen of our Frailties, he brought us into his Church, and there he took ſuch Care of us, that we are certain to be Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:36225:30"/>unleſs we wilfully refuſe to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the Remedies which he provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for us. He look'd upon us as his Neighbours: He Loved us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are made to the Divine Image, which, tho' defaced by Sin, and poſſeſs'd by the Devil, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs was ſtill capable of being Ranſom'd by the Merit of his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Renew'd by the Power of his Grace, and Perfected by the Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Glory. Theſe are the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons why our Saviour Loved us, even when we were his Enemies: For the ſame Reaſons we truly and juſtly Love our ſelves, in ſpite of all our Faults: And, tho' our Neighbour hates us, yet theſe Motives ſtill ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, and very well deſerve our Love.</p>
               <p>Let us therefore <hi>Love God</hi> above all things. Let us <hi>Love our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour</hi> as our ſelves. <hi>Love is the fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Law:</hi> Let us only <hi>Do this,</hi> and <hi>we ſhall live:</hi> Let us <hi>Do this,</hi> and <hi>we ſhall poſſeſs Eternal Life.</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="discourse">
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:36225:30"/>
            <head>Diſcourſe III. Of the Love of God, and the World.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>JEſus ſaid to his Diſciples: No Man can ſerve two Maſters: For either he will Hate the one, and Love the other; or elſe he will Hold to the one, and Deſpiſe the other. You cannot ſerve God and Mammon. Therefore I ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, Be not Solicitous for your Life, what you ſhall cat; nor yet for your Body, what you ſhall put on. Is not the Life more than Meat, and the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy more than Clothing? Behold the Fowls of the Air: For they Sow not, neither do they Reap, nor Gather into Barns; and yet your Heavenly Father Feeds them. Are not you much better than they? Which of you by taking Care can add one Cubit unto his Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? And why are you Solicitous for Clothing? Conſider the Lilies of the Field, how they Grow; they Toil not,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:36225:31"/>neither do they Spin. And yet I ſay unto you, that even</hi> Solomon <hi>in all his Glory was not arrayed like one of theſe. Wherefore if God ſo Clothe the Graſs of the Field, which to Day is, and to Morrow is caſt into the Oven, How much more will he Clothe you, O you of little Faith? Therefore be not Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citous, ſaying, What ſhall we Eat? Or what ſhall we Drink? Or where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withal ſhall we be Clothed? For af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all theſe things do the Gentiles ſeek. And your Father knows that you want all theſe things. Seek therefore Firſt the Kingdom of God, and his Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and all theſe things ſhall be added unto you.</hi> Math. 6. v. 24, to 34.</p>
            <p>This Goſpel teaches us Three Things. 1. That we <hi>cannot ſerve God and Mammon;</hi> we cannot ſerve <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>World;</hi> they cannot <hi>both</hi> be <hi>Maſters</hi> of our Heart and our Affections; but if we <hi>Love God,</hi> and <hi>hold to</hi> him above all things, we muſt of neceſſity either <hi>Hate</hi> the <hi>World,</hi> or at leaſt <hi>Deſpiſe</hi> it. 2. That it is
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:36225:31"/>a <hi>Dangerous</hi> thing to <hi>Love</hi> the World and be <hi>Solicitous</hi> for any thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to it; becauſe when <hi>Love</hi> is grown <hi>Solicitous</hi> 'tis certainly <hi>great,</hi> and the worſt of it is, we cannot certainly judge how <hi>great</hi> it is; it may, for ought we know, be <hi>grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> than the Love of God; and if it be ſo, we have already quitted the Service of <hi>God</hi> to Embrace the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the <hi>World.</hi> 3. That it is a <hi>needleſs</hi> thing to <hi>Love</hi> the World and be <hi>Solicitous</hi> for the neceſſary Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies of it; becauſe God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf has faithfully promis'd us, that as long as we make it our Chief Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>ſerve Him,</hi> He will always make it part of his Care, that the World ſhall be ſure to <hi>ſerve <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>If <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>World</hi> were both of the ſame Mind; if they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the ſame things, by the ſame Authority, and for the ſame End; they would not then be <hi>two Maſters</hi> Our Obedience to each of them
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:36225:32"/>would be one and the ſame thing; and, in obeying <hi>one,</hi> we ſhould obey them <hi>both.</hi> But this is an impoſſible Suppoſition. We all know very well, that God and the World are Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies which never can be reconciled. They command oppoſite things, by a different Authority, and for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Ends. The Laws of the World are directly Repugnant to the Laws of God: The uſurped Authority, by which they are impoſed, is derived originally from the Devil: And the Ends, they aim at, are as different as Temporal and Eternal.</p>
               <p>'Tis therefore impoſſible for God and the World, at the ſame time, to be each of them the Sovereign <hi>Maſter</hi> of our Heart. If we <hi>Hold to the one,</hi> we muſt <hi>Deſpiſe the other:</hi> If we <hi>Love the one,</hi> we muſt <hi>Hate the other:</hi> And ſince they are engaged in a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual <hi>War,</hi> we cannot Liſt our ſelves in <hi>Service</hi> of the <hi>one,</hi> without <hi>Fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> againſt the <hi>other.</hi> This is the Reaſon why <hi>our Life</hi> is ſaid to be a <hi>Warfare upon Earth.</hi> And this is
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:36225:32"/>the <hi>War</hi> which is deſcribed in the Epiſtle of this Day, betwixt the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> and the <hi>Spirit of this World,</hi> which are always <hi>contrary the one to the other.</hi> For which Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon S. <hi>James,</hi> in his Epiſtle, tells us, that the <hi>Friendſhip of this World is Enmity with God;</hi> and <hi>whoſoever will be the World's Friend, is God's Enemy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And yet although we cannot poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be Friends to <hi>both,</hi> we are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der an abſolute neceſſity of making Friends with <hi>one</hi> of them. The Reaſon is natural and evident. We are made to be happy; and indeed, happy we were, when we were Firſt made: But being unfortunately fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len from the Original Happineſs of our Firſt Creation, we feel the want of what we loſt; we cannot but be Conſcious of our Emptineſs; and therefore cannot help deſiring and endeavouring to ſatisfie it. Such is our Nature, that we <hi>muſt</hi> and <hi>will</hi> be happy, one way or other, if we <hi>can:</hi> And becauſe our Miſery and our
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:36225:33"/>Corruption are ſuch, that 'tis impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſible to find our Happineſs at home, 'Tis therefore no wonder that we go abroad to ſeek it. Now there are only two ſorts of Happineſs that we can think of; either our preſent Happineſs in this Life, or our future Happineſs in the next. <hi>God</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes the <hi>one:</hi> The <hi>World</hi> invites and tempts us to the <hi>other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>one</hi> is True and Sincere; the <hi>other</hi> Falſe and Counterfeit: The <hi>one</hi> Senſual and Beaſtly, the <hi>other</hi> Manly and Rational: The <hi>one</hi> Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixt and Pure, the <hi>other</hi> Sprinkled with Care and Sorrow: The <hi>one</hi> Secure and Eternal, the <hi>other</hi> ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liv'd and always dying, either with us, or before us. One would think that ſo much difference in the caſe, were more than enough to Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine our choice. And yet This is not All. Our God is ſo infinitely Good, ſo Merciful and Kind, that He not only promiſes All This <hi>here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after,</hi> but even <hi>here</hi> affords us ſo much Comfort Satisfaction and Pleaſure
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:36225:33"/>in a Vertuous Life, that the World with all its Charms, can never make a ſhew of any thing that's able to compare with it. He beſtows, at preſent, more Happineſs than the World can offer us; and, for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, He promiſes incomparably, nay infinitely, more than he now gives us: So that we are evidently Guilty of a double Folly, if we do not gladly accept of what we have in Hand, and thankfully ſubmit to give him Credit for the Reſt.</p>
               <p>Since therefore God has kindly left it to our choice, what <hi>Maſter</hi> we pleaſe to ſerve; and ſince we cannot avoid chuſing, let us grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and wiſely chuſe Himſelf. Let us ſerve him, becauſe he made us; let us love him, becauſe he lov'd us; let us live and die for him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he redeem'd us; let us obey him without reſerve, becauſe he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us without Meaſure. Let us baniſh the World from our Heart, and leave the whole room to Him, who only deſerves to be the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:36225:34"/>
                  <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Maſter</hi> of it. The World does not deſerve our Love, and therefore we ought to <hi>Deſpiſe</hi> it. On the contrary, it deſerves God's hatred, as well as ours; the Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ims of it are Inconſiſtent with his Service and our Happineſs; 'tis a declared Enemy to him, and a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious Enemy to us; and therefore we have a double Reaſon to <hi>Hate</hi> it.</p>
               <p>If we Love God above all things, the very Love of him is enough to ſet our Hearts at liberty: It diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arms the Power of the World: It makes us generouſly ſcorn its Riches, Vanities and Pleaſures: It calls home our Thoughts, reclaims our Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, calms our Paſſions, enlightens our Mind, enflames our Heart, and eſtabliſhes <hi>the Kingdom of God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in us.</hi> When once we Love God as we ought, we are <hi>led by the Spirit of God: And</hi> S. <hi>Paul</hi> aſſures us, that <hi>the Fruits of</hi> this <hi>Spirit</hi> are, not only <hi>Love,</hi> but <hi>Joy, Peace, Long-ſuffering, Gentleneſs, Goodneſs, Faith, Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Temperance,</hi> and all thoſe other
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:36225:34"/>Vertues which begin our <hi>Heaven</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it is not ſo with thoſe who Love this World above the next. They are Slaves to their own <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, Covetouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Pride:</hi> They begin their <hi>Hell,</hi> before they end their <hi>Lives:</hi> They wilſully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn themſelves, to all the Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, Anguiſhes, and Torments, which their eager, violent, and furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Paſſions can invent; and when theſe Executioners have done their worſt, <hi>the Devil and his Angels</hi> do the reſt for ever. They <hi>have receiv'd the Spirit of this World, whoſe Works,</hi> according to the ſame Apoſtle, <hi>are Manifeſt;</hi> not only <hi>Adultery, Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, Laſciviouſneſs, Drunkenneſs, and Revellings,</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>Covetouſneſs,</hi> which is <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and <hi>Pride,</hi> which naturally is attended with <hi>Hatred, Variances, Emulations, Anger, Strife, Seditions, Hereſies, Envyings, Murders, and ſuch like;</hi> concerning <hi>which,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel you, as I have alſo told you in
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:36225:35"/>time paſt, that they who do ſuch things ſhall not Inherit the Kingdom of God.</hi> No, no: They ſhall, whether they will or no, Inherit the Slavery of the <hi>Devil:</hi> But, as for the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> they have no Title to it. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs his <hi>Will be done,</hi> his <hi>Kingdom can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not come.</hi> Unleſs we Love him above all things, we cannot be his <hi>Subjects,</hi> nor can he be our <hi>King.</hi> Our <hi>Heart</hi> is the <hi>Throne</hi> of God: And when we begin to Balance betwixt him and the World, when we refuſe to let him Govern our Affections, we Rebel, we take up Arms againſt him, and call in the <hi>Devil</hi> to help us to <hi>Dethrone</hi> him. And can we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to <hi>inherit</hi> his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> if we wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully renounce it, and declare againſt it? Can we be <hi>Heirs</hi> of his Kingdom <hi>hereafter,</hi> if we are not Faithful and Loyal <hi>Subjects</hi> of it <hi>here?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>I have ſaid enough to ſhew the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility of ſerving <hi>two</hi> Maſters, the neceſſity of ſerving <hi>one,</hi> and the Folly of preferring the World before
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:36225:35"/>the Maker of it. I ſhall now conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the natural Conſequences of this Doctrine. If our preſent and future <hi>Happineſs</hi> depend entirely upon our <hi>Loving God</hi> above all things: If our <hi>Miſery,</hi> as well <hi>here</hi> as <hi>hereafter,</hi> is the Effect and Puniſhment of <hi>loving</hi> the <hi>World</hi> too much: It fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows evidently, that we ought to make it the Chief Buſineſs of our whole Life, to improve the <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and to leſſen the <hi>Love</hi> of this <hi>World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis true; the Kingdom of God is never perfect upon Earth: The Empire of Divine Love is never ſo abſolute here, as to exclude all Worldly Affection. The Love of this World is entail'd upon our Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted Nature: 'Tis an Inſeparable Companion of it, and a Mortal Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to it. And this is our unhappy Condition in this Vale of Miſery: We are engaged in a Continual War with our ſelves: Our Heart is the Field of Battel, where we <hi>muſt</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways <hi>Fight,</hi> and <hi>may</hi> always <hi>Conquer;</hi>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:36225:36"/>but <hi>can</hi> never <hi>Kill</hi> our Enemy. We can never quite deſtroy the Love of this World. Let us do what we can, 'twill never die before us: But as long as we live, 't will ſtill live in us; and whilſt it lives, will always ſtruggle with us, and rebel againſt us. But nevertheleſs, although we cannot Kill this Love, yet we can Moderate it, we can Weaken it, and keep it under: And this is what we are ſtrictly obliged to, unleſs we have a mind to Cheriſh our Danger, and to Periſh in it.</p>
               <p>This is the Reaſon why our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our had no ſooner ſaid to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, <hi>You cannot ſerve God and Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> but immediately he concludes, <hi>Therefore I ſay unto you, Be not Solici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous for</hi> this <hi>Life.</hi> And the Reaſon is clear: Becauſe when once we <hi>Love</hi> the <hi>World</hi> to that Degree, as to be <hi>Solicitous</hi> for it, we are in very great danger of <hi>loving</hi> the World <hi>too much,</hi> and of ſerving <hi>Mammon</hi> inſtead of <hi>God.</hi> I have already told you, that when <hi>Love</hi> is grown <hi>Solicitous,</hi> 'tis certainly
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:36225:36"/>
                  <hi>great;</hi> and that we cannot certainly judge <hi>how great</hi> it is. It may, for ought we know, be <hi>greater</hi> than the Love of God: And, if it be only <hi>as great,</hi> 'tis enough to loſe his Favour, and make him leave us to our ſelves, to ſeek our Fortune in the Service of this World.</p>
               <p>In Matters of little Importance, where our Heart is not much enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, we are not apt to be <hi>Solicitous;</hi> our Minds are at eaſe; we expect with a great deal of Patience, and are diſappointed with very little Diſturbance. But, if our Thoughts are always ſtirring and buſie, our Deſires eager and importune; if our Hopes are unquiet and reſtleſs, our Fears troubleſome and painful; if Delays very much mortifie us, and even the Apprehenſions of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointments very much diſturb us; we may be ſure that the <hi>Love,</hi> from whence all this <hi>Solicitude</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds, is <hi>very great:</hi> And, whether it be Honour, Intereſt or Pleaſure, be it what it will, 'tis certain we are
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:36225:37"/>
                  <hi>very much</hi> in <hi>Love</hi> with ſomething or other, which Influences all theſe Motions and Affections of our Mind and Heart; when things are once come to this paſs, 'tis time to look about us, and ſtand upon our Guard. We may hope indeed, that ſtill we Love God better than the World: And I muſt needs Confeſs, 'tis <hi>poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible</hi> we <hi>may;</hi> but I am ſure it is not very <hi>probable</hi> we <hi>do.</hi> There are great odds againſt us. For 'tis a certain Truth, that All our Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are proportion'd to the Love from whence they proceed: And if our Averſions and Deſires, our Hopes and Fears, our Joy and Grief, are ſtronger and more active in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns of this World, than in thoſe of Heaven, we have Reaſon to be very much afraid, that our Love of this World is greater than the Love of God.</p>
               <p>'Tis a groſs Miſtake to imagine, that becauſe we ſtill <hi>Eſteem</hi> God <hi>more,</hi> Therefore we <hi>Love</hi> him <hi>better.</hi> Alas! This <hi>Eſteem</hi> is only a Compliment
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:36225:37"/>of our <hi>Mind:</hi> And this Compliment may eaſily paſs for Current, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho' the ſtrongeſt Affections of our Heart are otherwiſe engaged. We know too well by ſad Experience, that there is a certain thing call'd <hi>Humour,</hi> which often over-rules our <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and ſteals away our <hi>Heart</hi> to doat upon thoſe very Follies, which, in our Serious Thoughts, we cannot but deſpiſe. A Man who is <hi>Solicitous</hi> for this World, may eaſily deceive himſelf in this Matter. He may <hi>Eſteem</hi> God a great deal more, and yet <hi>Love</hi> him a great deal leſs. <hi>The Diſciples</hi> had a great <hi>Eſteem</hi> of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> and thought they <hi>loved</hi> him better than their Lives: They <hi>All</hi> declared they would rather <hi>die with</hi> him, than <hi>deny</hi> him: And yet, immediately after, the Chief of them <hi>denied him,</hi> and <hi>all the</hi> reſt <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook him.</hi> When they look'd upon the time of Trial at a diſtance, they had a great Opinion of their Strength: But when the Occaſion was preſent, they ſoon diſcover'd
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:36225:38"/>their Weakneſs. This was once their Caſe: And God only knows how often it has been ours.</p>
               <p>Their Caſe, you'll ſay, was diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent; becauſe they were Guilty of a great Preſumption. But pray con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider a little. Are not we as guilty as they? Do we not preſume as much? Are we not as confident of our own Strength? We know very well, that the <hi>Love</hi> of this <hi>World</hi> is a Mortal Enemy to the <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>God:</hi> And therefore, if we do not daily watch the Motions of this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, oppoſe its Progreſs, and cut off all Communications which may any way Fortifie it; if on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, we daily furniſh it with all Proviſions, Ammunitions, and Arms, againſt us; if we thus <hi>deſpiſe</hi> the <hi>Strength</hi> of our Enemy; is it not Viſible, that we too much <hi>confide</hi> in in our <hi>own?</hi> And if we commonly <hi>neglect</hi> thoſe daily Conſiderations, Exerciſes and Endeavours, which are neceſſary to Encreaſe and Fortifie the Love of God; is not this a down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:36225:38"/>
                  <hi>Preſumption</hi> in our own Suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency, as if we already <hi>loved</hi> him <hi>enough?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Remember the Fall of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. Remember how grievouſly they were miſtaken. Remember that not only their Doctrines, but even their Failings, ought to be an Inſtruction to us. Never let us <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fide</hi> in our preſent Love of God; but let us daily endeavour to <hi>Improve</hi> it. Never let us <hi>deſpiſe</hi> the Strength of our Worldly Love; but let us dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly endeavour to <hi>abate</hi> it. If we could <hi>ſerve two Maſters,</hi> we might be <hi>Solicitous</hi> for <hi>both:</hi> But ſince we can only <hi>ſerve One,</hi> 'tis a dangerous thing to be <hi>Solicitous</hi> for any <hi>Other. You cannot ſerve God and Mammon,</hi> ſays our Saviour; <hi>therefore I ſay unto you, Be not Solicitous for this Life.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>We have ſeen how <hi>Dangerous</hi> it is, to be <hi>Solicitous</hi> for any thing in this World: The reſt of the Goſpel ſhews us, that his <hi>Solicitude</hi> is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:36225:39"/>
                  <hi>needleſs.</hi> If there were any ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of it, our Saviour would not forbid it. The Words are plain, <hi>Be not Solicitous for your Life.</hi> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, if we <hi>ſeek firſt the Kingdom of God,</hi> if the Service of God be truly and ſincerely our firſt and principal Concern, 'tis evidently <hi>needleſs</hi> to be <hi>Solicitous</hi> for our <hi>Life.</hi> He made us for himſelf; and for his own ſake he takes care of us. Not that he is any way the better for us, but becauſe he naturally takes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in doing good to All, who do not wilfully oppoſe the overflowing of his Goodneſs. He gave us our Life, that, if we pleaſe, we may be Happy, by employing it entirely in his Service: And as long as we ſerve the Maſter who gave us this Life, our Self-preſervation is in better Hands than our own. All the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of Men and Devils put together, can never take away our Life, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out our Maſter's order, or his leave: And therefore whenſoever, either by his leave, or by his order, the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:36225:39"/>Hour of our Death ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, we may be aſſur'd our Maſter has no more occaſion for our Service; and therefore we have no Pretenſions to Live longer. There is only <hi>One thing Neceſſary</hi> in this World, and that's our <hi>Duty</hi> to our Maſter: And, whenſoever our <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> ſtands in Competition with our <hi>Life,</hi> if we are true and faithful Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, we ſhall always readily and cheerfully conclude; <hi>Our Duty is Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, but our Life is not.</hi> When things are in this poſture, 'tis evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that the Obſervance of <hi>this Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> is the <hi>laſt</hi> Piece of <hi>Service</hi> which our <hi>Maſter</hi> requires at our Hands: And ſince <hi>our Service</hi> is the <hi>End</hi> for which <hi>our Life</hi> was given us, if we wiſh to out-live our <hi>Service,</hi> we are every jot as unreaſonable, as if we wiſh'd to out-live the <hi>End</hi> of <hi>our Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You'll tell me perhaps, you are very willing to Die when God plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: But you are afraid of wanting the Neceſſary Conveniences of Humane Life, and therefore you are juſtly
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:36225:40"/>
                  <hi>Solicitous,</hi> for fear of being Miſerable whilſt you Live. And truly you are partly in the right. You have all the Reaſon in the World to be willing that God ſhould chuſe the Hour, and appoint the Moment of your Death; becauſe He only knows what Time is beſt and fitteſt for us. But ſince we are willing to truſt him with our <hi>Life,</hi> why ſhould we not as willingly truſt him with <hi>all things elſe</hi> belonging to it? He has promis'd to take Care of us. He knows, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than we do, what is good for us. He loves us better than we love our ſelves. His Power is boundleſs, and cannot be obſtructed. Is not this enough to ſecure us? He is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely Powerful: <hi>He is able, ſays S.</hi> Paul, <hi>to do exceeding abundantly, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all that we can ask or think.</hi> He is infinitely Good: He cannot but Delight in being ſo, to thoſe that ſerve him. He is infinitely Wiſe: He cannot commit the leaſt miſtake in our Concerns. In a Word, his <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> his <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> and his <hi>Power,</hi>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:36225:40"/>all concurr to Enſure the Bleſſings of his <hi>Providence,</hi> which by a Solemn <hi>Promiſe</hi> is engaged for ever, to be favourable to us. <hi>Seek firſt the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, and his Righteouſneſs, and All theſe things ſhall be added to you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 'Tis the Voice of <hi>Truth</hi> it ſelf: <hi>Truth</hi> cannot tell a <hi>Lie:</hi> His <hi>Promiſe</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not fail.</p>
               <p>Is it not the <hi>Firſt</hi> Article of our Creed, to <hi>believe in God the Father Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty?</hi> Does not the <hi>Firſt</hi> of all our Petitions begin with theſe comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Words, <hi>Our Father who art in Heaven?</hi> If we believe him to be <hi>Our Father,</hi> ought we not to believe that he will certainly be careful of his <hi>Children?</hi> And if we really be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve He is always careful of us, what <hi>need</hi> we at any time be Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>careful and <hi>Solicitous</hi> for our ſelves. <hi>Therefore I ſay unto you,</hi> ſays our Saviour, <hi>Be not Solicitous for your Life, what you ſhall eat; nor yet for your Body, what you ſhall put on.</hi> He only forbids our being <hi>Solicitous.</hi> He does not forbid us to <hi>Work</hi> and <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour</hi>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:36225:41"/>for an Honeſt Livelyhood. <hi>Our Heavenly Father</hi> does not encourage Idleneſs in his Children. He ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects that we ſhould be induſtrious in doing of our part: And, when we have done that, He's always ready to ſupply the reſt. And to ſatisfie us concerning this matter, our Saviour is not contented to give us his bare Word for it, but uſes ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Arguments in order to convince us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is not the Life more than Meat,</hi> ſays he, <hi>and the Body more than Clothing?</hi> He who freely and frankly beſtows upon us what is <hi>more,</hi> will he deny us what is <hi>leſs?</hi> Do we not all of us Value our <hi>Body</hi> more than our <hi>Clothing,</hi> and our <hi>Life</hi> more than <hi>Meat?</hi> And can we think that He, who voluntarily grants theſe grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Benefits, will grudge us others which are much Inferiour to them? He gave us our <hi>Body,</hi> and Breath'd <hi>Life</hi> into it. What mov'd him to be ſo kind? He might have done as he pleas'd. Before we lived, we could
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:36225:41"/>not deſerve our <hi>Life;</hi> nor could we ſo much as ask it. Since therefore He beſtow'd this Great and Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Bleſſing upon us, without either deſerving or asking it; may we not firmly believe, He will never deny us other leſſer Bleſſings, when we not only <hi>ask</hi> them, but make it our Chief Buſineſs to <hi>deſerve</hi> them, by ſpending our whole <hi>Life</hi> in his Service?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Behold the Fowls of the Air,</hi> ſays he, <hi>they ſow not, neither do they reap, nor gather into Barns.</hi> They are Idle and Careleſs; they do nothing for themſelves; and nevertheleſs <hi>our Heavenly Father feeds them.</hi> He is not <hi>their</hi> Father, <hi>and yet be feeds them:</hi> And will he refuſe to <hi>feed us,</hi> becauſe he is <hi>our Father?</hi> Will he not help us when we have done the Duty of good <hi>Children,</hi> by endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to help our ſelves? Will he do <hi>all</hi> for <hi>them,</hi> and <hi>nothing</hi> for <hi>us?</hi> Have we not Reaſon to believe, He Loves his <hi>better</hi> Creatures <hi>beſt?</hi> And
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:36225:42"/>does he not plainly tell us, <hi>we are much better than they?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which of you,</hi> ſays our Saviour, <hi>by taking Care, can add one Cubit to his Stature?</hi> No Man ever grew Taller, by <hi>wiſhing</hi> to be ſo: Neither has any Man ever been Happier, by being <hi>Solicitous</hi> about it. This Compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhews plainly, that <hi>Solicitude</hi> never does good; and that therefore there is never any <hi>need</hi> of it. When we have done what's fitting, and have taken Care to do as much as we ought, 'tis Vain and Fooliſh to entertain any further Concern, and be <hi>Solicitous</hi> for the Event of our Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours. We have <hi>planted,</hi> we have <hi>water'd,</hi> we have done our <hi>part:</hi> The <hi>encreaſe</hi> belongs to God; and what have we to do with <hi>his</hi> Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? Let him do as he pleaſes; and let us be Contented with his Holy Will and Pleaſure. If we truly Love him above all things, it will not be ſo hard, to like that <hi>moſt,</hi> which he likes <hi>beſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After theſe, and other Arguments,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:36225:42"/>our Saviour concludes, <hi>Therefore be not Solicitous, ſaying, What ſhall we Eat, or what ſhall we Drink or where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withal ſhall we be Clothed? For af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all theſe things do the Gentiles ſeek.</hi> If we were <hi>Gentiles;</hi> if we were <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens;</hi> if we had <hi>no</hi> Knowledge of <hi>God;</hi> then indeed it were no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that we <hi>ſeek theſe things,</hi> and are <hi>Solicitous</hi> about them: But ſince <hi>our Father knows</hi> a great deal better than we do, how <hi>much,</hi> how <hi>long,</hi> and to what <hi>End,</hi> we <hi>want theſe things;</hi> ſince we believe in his All-ſeeing and All-ruling <hi>Providence;</hi> ſince we know very well, that <hi>all theſe things</hi> are only neceſſary during Life, and that our Life is neceſſary no longer than God requires our Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; ſince, I ſay, by Faith we are inſtructed ſo much better than the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> is it not a Scandalous and a Notorious Shame, that all the World is Witneſs of our ſeeming e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very jot as Eager and <hi>Solicitous</hi> as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the <hi>Heathens</hi> were? If we ſerve <hi>Mammon</hi> like <hi>Heathens;</hi> how can we at the ſame time ſerve <hi>God</hi> like <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians?</hi>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:36225:43"/>The Goſpel plainly declares in the beginning, <hi>we cannot ſerve two Maſters<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> God and the World: And, in the end it aſſures us, that if <hi>we ſeek firſt the Kingdom of God, All theſe things ſhall be added to us.</hi> The only way, to be truly <hi>Maſters</hi> of this <hi>World,</hi> is to be True and Faithful <hi>Servants</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> Let us therefore, in the <hi>firſt</hi> place be careful to <hi>ſerve God.</hi> All other Care is <hi>dangerous,</hi> and <hi>needleſs.</hi> Let us only ſerve <hi>Him;</hi> and <hi>He</hi> will certainly take Care, that the <hi>World</hi> ſhall <hi>ſerve us,</hi> and conduct us, eaſily and ſafely from his <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> upon <hi>Earth,</hi> to his <hi>Kingdom</hi> in <hi>Heaven, which was prepared for us from the Foundation of the World.</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="discourse">
            <head>Diſcourſe IV. Of Worldly Policy, and Chriſtian Prudence.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THE</hi> Phariſees <hi>went and conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted together how they might
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:36225:43"/>Catch Jeſus in his Diſcourſe. And they ſend unto him their Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples with the</hi> Herodians, <hi>ſaying, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, we know that thou art true, and teacheſt the Way of God in Truth, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doſt thou care for any Man, for thou regardeſt not the Perſons of Men. Tell us therefore, What thinkeſt thou? Is it lawful to give Tribute unto</hi> Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar, <hi>or not? But Jeſus perceiving their Malice, ſaid, Why do ye Tempt me, ye Hypocrites? Shew me the Tribute-Money. And they brought unto him a Penny. And he ſaith unto them, Whoſe is this Image and Superſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? They ſay unto him,</hi> Caeſar<hi>'s. Then ſays he unto them, Render there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore unto</hi> Caeſar <hi>the things which are due to</hi> Caeſar, <hi>and unto God the things which are due to God.</hi> Matth. 22. v. 15, to 22.</p>
            <p>There's nothing ſo Wiſe, ſo Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable, and Juſt, as Chriſtian Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence: And nothing, on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, ſo Fooliſh, ſo Malicious, and Unjuſt, as Worldly Policy.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:36225:44"/>
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>Idolatry is the height of Folly. 'Tis ſo extravagantly Fooliſh, that many People can ſcarce believe there was ever any ſuch thing in the World. They are ſo incredulous in this Point, that common Hiſtory will not ſatisfie them, but we are forced to have Recourſe to <hi>Scripture,</hi> to convince them. For Example. We read in <hi>Exodus,</hi> how <hi>they made a Molten Calf, and worſhipt it, and ſacrificed unto it.</hi> In <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> we read, <hi>they ſacrificed to Devils, not to God.</hi> In the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> we read, how common it was amongſt them, for a <hi>Carpenter</hi> to <hi>make a God, and worſhip it: He burns part of it in the Fire,</hi> ſays the Prophet, <hi>and the reſidue thereof he makes a God: he falls down to it, and Worſhips it, and Prays to it, and ſays, Deliver me, for thou art my God.</hi> In doing thus, the Scripture aſſures us, <hi>they forgot God their Saviour;</hi> they <hi>forgot me, ſaith the Lord,</hi> and <hi>did not know that I gave them Corn, and Wine, and Oyl,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:36225:44"/>and Multiplied</hi> their <hi>Silver and Gold which they prepared for</hi> Baal. And therefore 'tis clear, they did not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect their Worſhip to <hi>God,</hi> whom <hi>they forgot;</hi> but as the Prophet <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy</hi> tells us, they <hi>turn'd their Back to God,</hi> and their <hi>Face</hi> to Idols, <hi>ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a Stock, thou art my Father, and to a Stone, thou haſt brought me forth.</hi> I muſt confeſs, all this is ſo intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably ſilly, that, unleſs the Word of God aſſerted it, I could not eaſily believe it. And yet I am fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that if we Examine well the Depth of Humane Policy, and ſearch the Foundation of it, we ſhall find it grounded upon as groſs Idolatry as this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt have no other Gods before me,</hi> ſays our Lord, in the firſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment. And in the Explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it, he inſtances in thoſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Gods which then were moſt in Faſhion, <hi>Thou ſhalt not make unto thee any Graven Image, Thou ſhalt not Bow down thy ſelf to them, nor Worſhip them.</hi> Thus he forbids the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:36225:45"/>
                  <hi>Worſhip</hi> of <hi>other Gods,</hi> both <hi>all</hi> and <hi>ſome.</hi> And now I deſire to know whether it be not too true, that all thoſe Worldly Politicians are I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolaters, who <hi>ſeek firſt the Kingdom of</hi> this World, and expect that the <hi>Kingdom of God</hi> ſhould be <hi>added to</hi> them? Do they not <hi>change the Truth of God into a Lie, and Worſhip the Creature more than the Creator?</hi> Do they not <hi>make</hi> to themſelves <hi>a Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Image?</hi> Do they not frame to themſelves an imaginary Happineſs? A Happineſs which is not to be had <hi>in Heaven above,</hi> but only <hi>in the Earth beneath?</hi> And do they not <hi>bow down and ſerve it?</hi> How many are there of whom S. <hi>Paul</hi> makes mention, <hi>whoſe Belly is their God,</hi> who Sacrifice themſelves to Glutto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and Drunkenneſs, and waſte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their Lives in Flames of Luſt? Their ſhort-liv'd Happineſs is <hi>part of it</hi> dead already, <hi>and burnt in</hi> its own <hi>Fire;</hi> and of <hi>the reſidue thereof,</hi> they ſtill perſiſt to <hi>make a God, and Worſhip it.</hi> How many are there
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:36225:45"/>in the World, who are ready at any time to Pawn their Souls for Gold? Do not theſe Men <hi>make a</hi> Golden <hi>Calf, and Worſhip it?</hi> Thoſe Men who quit their Religion to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure their Fortune; who do not think there is a Thouſand Pounds a Year difference betwixt the <hi>Right</hi> and the <hi>Wrong;</hi> but prefer the ſhort Enjoyment of a little Spot of <hi>Terra Firma,</hi> before the Everlaſting Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their Heavenly Inheritance; do not theſe Men make a God of <hi>Mammon?</hi> Do they not put more Confidence in their Eſtate, than in the God of Heaven and Earth? Do they not <hi>forget God their Saviour,</hi> as if they <hi>did not know that</hi> he <hi>gave them</hi> all theſe things? Do they not <hi>turn their Back to God,</hi> and their <hi>Face</hi> to Idols, <hi>ſaying to</hi> their Land, <hi>thou art our Father,</hi> to thee we owe our Lives, <hi>and to</hi> their Money, <hi>thou haſt brought us forth,</hi> and deliver'd us <hi>out of the Houſe of Bondage?</hi> How many are there who are ſuch Idolaters of Worldly Honour, that they tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:36225:46"/>under Foot the Laws of God and Man, the Laws Eccleſiaſtical and Civil, rather than ſeem to Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, in the leaſt punctilio, againſt the Laws of Hectoriſm? They pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer thoſe Maxims, which the Pride of <hi>Lucifer</hi> has introudced and ſettled in the World, before the Precepts of the Moſt High God, which are reveal'd, confirm'd, and ratified un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, by the Goſpel, Church, and State. The very Thought of being Laught at, and Deſpiſed by ſome few ſilly People, for a little while, is much more Terrible to them, than the Loſs of God, and all that's Good, for all Eternity. When once the Reputation of their Modiſh Bravery is call'd in queſtion by the leaſt Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front or Provocation, they are ſo bewitch'd, ſo ſtupified, ſo over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>power'd, with a Baſe, Cowardly Fear of loſing it, that altho' they are daring enough to Die Eternally for it, they have not true Courage e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to live one Moment without it. They <hi>Sacrifice to Devils, not to God.</hi>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:36225:46"/>They force their way thro' Blood and Aſhes, to the Altars of Revenge and Pride. They imprint and <hi>grave</hi> in their Minds <hi>an Image</hi> of I know not what, which none but Fools call <hi>Honour,</hi> and to this they offer up their Vows and Prayers; they <hi>fall down to it, and worſhip it, and</hi> in their Hearts <hi>they ſay unto it, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver us, for thou art our God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Pſalmiſt tells us, that <hi>the Fool ſays,</hi> in his Heart, <hi>There is no God.</hi> And truly, if we well conſider the matter, we ſhall find that all thoſe People, who <hi>ſeek firſt the Kingdom of this World,</hi> the Honours, Riches, and Pleaſures of it, are certainly ſuch <hi>Fools,</hi> as to <hi>ſay, in their Heart, There is no</hi> other <hi>God</hi> but theſe. 'Tis no wonder therefore that the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>The Wiſdom of this World is Fooliſhneſs with God.</hi> No wonder that he tells the Politicians of this World, that they are <hi>vain in their imaginations;</hi> that <hi>their fooliſh Hearts are darkned;</hi> and that <hi>profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing themſelves Wiſe,</hi> as really they
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:36225:47"/>are, in the management of Worldly Affairs, <hi>they become Fools</hi> in the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>government of themſelves.</p>
               <p>When I talk of Politicians, I do not only mean thoſe great Ones, who ſit at the Helm of Government, Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical or Civil; I alſo Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend all thoſe, who, in the Shades of a Private Life, find warmth enough to nouriſh Pride and Luxury, as well as Covetouſneſs. Alas! It is not the Palace or the Cottage that makes any great difference in the Caſe: 'Tis the Heart of Man which is the Temple of theſe Idols: And the loweſt Condition we can think of, does not hinder us from loving our ſelves above all things, and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizing ſuch little Deities as our nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Capacity can afford us. 'Tis not the Golden or the Wooden Idol that aggravates or leſſens the Crime: 'Tis the Worſhip that makes the Idolater. We know very well, that Villages retain'd their Pagan-Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, when the greater Cities ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd it. We certainly know, that
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:36225:47"/>altho' Self-love and Pride are bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs in their vaſt Pretenſions, yet they play at ſmall Game rather than ſit out. And therefore 'tis no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if the Poor, as well as Rich, are apt to Idolize themſelves, and ſo <hi>are give <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ver to a Reprobate Mind, Proud, Coverous, without Natural Affection, Deceitful, Envious, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmerciful,</hi> in a word, <hi>Malicious,</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>If I did not very well Conſider the prodigious <hi>Folly</hi> of Self-love, I could not believe it capable of ſo much <hi>Malice.</hi> Who could have imagin'd, if the Scriptures were not plain, that the <hi>Jews</hi> who had ſo long expected the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> could be ſo <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious</hi> againſt him, when he came? He came from Heaven; and this perhaps was more than they expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. He was True God, as well as Man; and this, I fear, was more than they deſired. He came to <hi>ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil the Law,</hi> and to make them <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect</hi> like their <hi>Father in Heaven;</hi> and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:36225:48"/>this was a great deal too much, for thoſe who thought themſelves al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready good enough. But yet me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks they had no reaſon to like him ſo much worſe, for being ſo much better than their wiſhes. His only fault was, that he was to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> good for them; and becauſe he was ſo, therefore they could not abide him. He came <hi>to deſtroy the Works of the Devil;</hi> to pull down <hi>the Idols</hi> which they had <hi>ſet up</hi> in their Hearts; and teach them <hi>to Adore,</hi> the One True God <hi>in Spirit and Truth,</hi> by taking away the Worſhip of all Worldly Honours, Wealth and Pleaſures. <hi>Learn of me,</hi> ſays he, <hi>becauſe I am humble of Heart.</hi> Learn of me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Bleſſed are the Poor in Spirit.</hi> Learn of me, becauſe <hi>Bleſſed are they who are Perſecuted for Righteouſneſs ſake.</hi> Learn all this, and always re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member this comfortable Leſſon, <hi>Theirs is the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> Let this be always the Treaſure of your Minds; let it always be the Cordial of your Hearts; remember it was I
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:36225:48"/>my ſelf that told you, <hi>Theirs is the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This was <hi>the Light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt;</hi> but this Light <hi>did not ſhine upon them,</hi> ſo as to open their Eyes, becauſe <hi>they loved</hi> the <hi>Darkneſs</hi> they were in: <hi>The God of this World</hi> had <hi>blinded their Minds:</hi> And they <hi>hated the Light becauſe their Works were Evil.</hi> Alas! They did not care for the <hi>Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> An Earthly Kingdom was the chief thing they deſired. They expected the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> to Redeem them from the Slavery of their Enemies, to En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich them with the Spoils of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd Nations, and to make the whole World Tributary to them. They loved themſelves too well, to care for any thing elſe; and loved this World too much, to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd for any other. Their Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was to build their Tabernacles here: The great Employment of their Minds was to contrive a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice on Earth: And their whole Souls were taken up with ſtriving
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:36225:49"/>to be Rich and Powerful, that they might purchaſe and command what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Pleaſures they deſir'd. And therefore when the <hi>Meſſiab</hi> came to undeceive them, they were ſo ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized, they could not believe he was the Perſon whom they had ſo long expected. They did not imagine, his deſign was only to Redeem them from the Slavery of Sin, to aſſiſt them in the Conqueſt of their Vices, and to make their Paſſions Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary to their Reaſon. The Objects of theſe Paſſions were the <hi>Idols,</hi> which they had ſo long Adored, and Worſhipt with as furious a Zeal as any of the <hi>Heathens round about them;</hi> and theſe they would not part with, upon any Terms: They would not endure to have them Abandon'd, Undervalued and Deſpiſed: <hi>No, no, ſay they, We will not have this Man Reign over us.</hi> And thus you plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee, 'twas their <hi>Idolatry,</hi> which made them ſo blindly <hi>Zealous;</hi> 'twas their prodigious <hi>Folly,</hi> which made them ſo ſtrangely <hi>Malicious</hi> againſt him.</p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:36225:49"/>
               <p>We read in our preſent Goſpel, that <hi>the Phariſees went and Conſulted together,</hi> how they might <hi>Catch him in his Diſcourſe.</hi> His <hi>Actions</hi> they could not Condemn: He <hi>went about, doing good</hi> to all: He was in all things a living Example of Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: But however, their <hi>Malice</hi> made them hope to <hi>Catch him,</hi> and <hi>lay hold of</hi> ſome unwary <hi>Words</hi> in <hi>his Diſcourſe.</hi> This was not the firſt Onſet: We read in the forego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chapter, how <hi>they ſought to lay hands on him,</hi> but durſt not, becauſe they feared the <hi>Multitude, who took him for a Prophet.</hi> They durſt not meddle with him: And therefore away <hi>they went, and Conſulted toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther how to Catch him</hi> another time. We read in S. <hi>Luke,</hi> how <hi>they watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, and ſent forth Spies, to feign themſelves Juſt Men, that they might take hold of his Words, that ſo they might deliver him to the Power of the Governour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They <hi>feigned themſelves Juſt.</hi> They knew well enough the true Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:36225:50"/>of Goodneſs: But the <hi>Malice</hi> of their Hearts abuſed the beſt and cleareſt Light of their Minds. They knew how to act their part; but could not endure the ſincere pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of it. A wicked Man is always the worſe for his Knowledge: The more he has, the more cunning he is in making ill uſe of it, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying it againſt his Neighbour, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of improving it to himſelf. They knew very well the Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of a Prophet ſent by God: <hi>Maſter,</hi> ſay they, <hi>we know that thou art true, and teacheſt the way of God in truth, neither doſt thou care for any Man, for thou regardeſt not the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Men.</hi> They appeal'd to his Integrity, to decide the Rights of <hi>Caeſar</hi> and the <hi>People.</hi> They knew how hard it was to pleaſe both Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and how dangerous to give of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to either. They wanted the aſſiſtance of the one, or other, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy him. The <hi>Multitude</hi> took his part, becauſe <hi>they took him for a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet.</hi> The <hi>Emperor</hi> had nothing to
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:36225:50"/>ſay againſt him, ſo long as he did not meddle with the Government. And therefore the only Comfort of their Malice, was the Hope they had to make him chuſe one ſide, that they might make him odious to the other.</p>
               <p>There is nothing ſo Raſh and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprizing as Vanity. A Man who is poſſeſs'd with a greedy deſire of Popular Eſteem, will ſtick at no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to Purchaſe it. The <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees</hi> by Experience knew the force of it. The Goſpel tells us how they <hi>loved</hi> to do things <hi>to be ſeen by Men.</hi> And therefore they cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly endeavour'd to inſinuate how much they admir'd their <hi>Maſter</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, and that nothing could Crown his Merit with a greater Addition of Glory, than his being bold enough to Declare againſt <hi>Caeſar. Tell us therefore,</hi> ſay they, <hi>What thinkeſt thou? Is it Lawful to give Tribute to</hi> Caeſar, <hi>or not?</hi> Do but tell us boldly, that we, who are God's People, are free from Tribute, and that it is not
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:36225:51"/>Lawful to pay it to <hi>Caeſar:</hi> Tell us only this, and we ſhall all of us Conclude, That no Man ever gave a greater inſtance of his <hi>Teaching the way of God in Truth,</hi> without <hi>caring for any Man,</hi> and without <hi>regarding the Perſons of Men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus they maliciouſly contrive his Ruin, whilſt he kindly aims at no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but their Good. They flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, and try to entangle him, whilſt he deals ſincerely with them, and makes it his buſineſs to unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them. They praiſe his Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity, with a wicked intention, to make him Proud and Indiſcreet, whilſt he diſcovers their Hypocriſie, with a Charitable Deſign, to make them Wiſe and Humble. <hi>He per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived their Malice,</hi> and thus Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulated with them, <hi>Why do ye tempt me, ye Hypocrites?</hi> Why are you ſo <hi>fooliſh,</hi> as to <hi>have other Gods before me,</hi> and only <hi>feign your ſelves Juſt,</hi> in preſence of him, who, by ſo many Miracles, has proved, he is the One True God, who ſees th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Secrets of
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:36225:51"/>your Hearts? Why are you ſo <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious,</hi> as to ſeek the Ruin of a Man, who comes from Heaven to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem you, and to Save you from Eternal Miſery? Why are you ſo <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt,</hi> to God, your Neighbour, and your Selves?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>What was it that made the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens ſo <hi>Malicious</hi> againſt the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians? What made them ſo <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt</hi> in perſecuting, as to lay aſide all Rules and Forms of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice? The Principal and Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental reaſon was, becauſe the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith oppoſed the Worſhip of their Gods. <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy</hi> tells us, That <hi>when they were Indicted as Criminals, they were not vouchſafed the Juſtice of Legal Trials.</hi> They were Tortur'd after they Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd; they were not heard in their own Defence; they were denied all benefit of the Law; and, after all, they were not allow'd to offer their Humble and Dutiful Petitions to
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:36225:52"/>their Prince, for any Redreſs. Such Proceedings as theſe, were not only contrary to the received Laws of the Empire, but againſt the Common Liberties of Humanity and Nature, and the Allowance of all Juſt Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments. In other matters they obſerved ſome meaſures of Equity: But, when their Idols were oppoſed, their Paſſion baniſh'd all manner of Reaſon, and left no Room for Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</p>
               <p>This is the common Caſe of all Self-lovers. They are <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt</hi> to God, whoſe Worſhip they give to his Creatures; <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt</hi> to their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, whoſe Concerns they Sacrifice to their own; and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt</hi> to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, whoſe Body and Soul they Damn for all Eternity. We read in Scripture, <hi>He that is Evil to himſelf, to whom will he be Good?</hi> He that Loves himſelf above all things, is as Evil to himſelf as his Hands and Heart can make him: How then will he be good to any Body elſe? How will he ſpare his Neighbour's
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:36225:52"/>Blood before the Altar of that Idol, to which he Daily Sacrifices his own Soul, his Heart, and All that is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in him? When once the Devil has poſſeſs'd Mens Fancies with a great Idea of this World, and led them by Degrees to that <hi>exceeding height,</hi> from whence <hi>he ſhews</hi> them <hi>all the</hi> Happineſs, and <hi>Glory of it;</hi> when once they reliſh the fond Hopes of <hi>all theſe things,</hi> the Honors, Wealth, and Pleaſures of this World; when once their Hearts are fixt upon theſe Idols of their Mind; there is no longer any Juſtice to be had, no Right to be pleaded, no Law to be acknowledg'd, but the Sovereign Will and Pleaſure of Self-love. They may counterfeit Piety, Loyalty, Friendſhip, Juſtice, Liberality, and all thoſe Virtues which are Popular and Serviceable to their Politick De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns; they may poſſibly have ſome Degree of Natural Goodneſs, and may act ſincerely in ſome ſmall Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, where 'tis no way incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the Worſhip of their
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:36225:53"/>Idols; they may <hi>feign themſelves Juſt</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> to a <hi>Friend</hi> or <hi>Neighbour,</hi> and all theſe Vertues may perhaps look well enough in the Face; but, whereſoever Self-love Lives and Reigns, it is impoſſible to have them ſound at Heart. Theſe Duties peradventure may obtain ſome Toleration at a diſtance; but muſt never approach the Altar, where Self-love has placed the <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Image</hi> of their Happineſs. 'Tis true, the Honours, Riches and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures here below, are all imaginary things; there's nothing Real and Subſtantial in them: And, when the parting Hour draws near, when once theſe drouſie Souls are thoroughly awaken'd with a quick and lively Sence of their Eternity, they then ſee clearly the illuſion, and the emptineſs of all theſe ſilly Dreams. But nevertheleſs they now are ſo Amus'd and Charm'd, with an imagination of ſomething or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in which they place their Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, that, whatſoe'er it is, they
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:36225:53"/>
                  <hi>make a God</hi> of it, <hi>they Adore and Serve it only.</hi> All their other Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, whatſoe'er they are, muſt all <hi>bow down</hi> to this: And all the <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> of a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> of a <hi>Subject,</hi> of a <hi>Friend,</hi> or <hi>Neighbour,</hi> muſt be Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed as often as they dare pretend to ſtand in competition with it.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the Natural Effects of <hi>Worldly Policy;</hi> the neceſſary Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences of that <hi>Wiſdom of this World,</hi> which, the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>is Fooliſhneſs with God.</hi> 'Tis <hi>Fooliſh</hi> in it ſelf, <hi>Malicious</hi> againſt it oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt</hi> to all. And truly we can expect no better, if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that the firſt Principles of it, are an inſatiable Self-love, a vain <hi>Hope</hi> of Self-enjoyment, and a ſilly <hi>Belief,</hi> that this miſerable World is the only Seat of Happineſs.</p>
               <p>On the contrary, <hi>Chriſtian Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> the firſt of Moral Vertues, which Directs and Governs the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of them all, is grounded upon the Three Theological Vertues, a true <hi>Love of God</hi> above all things, a
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:36225:54"/>comfortable <hi>Hope</hi> of Enjoying him for ever, and a lively <hi>Faith</hi> that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe can make us truly Happy. Theſe are the Fundamental Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of <hi>Chriſtian Prudence,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is nothing ſo truly Wiſe, ſo Charitable, and ſo Juſt.</p>
               <p n="1">1. There is nothing ſo <hi>Wiſe.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as Self-preſervation is the firſt Inſtinct of Nature, ſo true Self-love is the firſt Effect of Divine Wiſdom; and Chriſtian Prudence teaches us the true Love of our ſelves. It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards our true Intereſt and Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; it endeavours to free us from our greateſt Evils, and procure our greateſt Good; it conſiders, that inward Peace is better than outward Eaſe, that our Souls are nobler than our Bodies, that Eternity is infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more conſiderable than Time; that the <hi>ſhort</hi> and <hi>light Afflictions</hi> of this World, <hi>which are but for a Moment,</hi> are nothing in compariſon of <hi>Everlaſting</hi> and <hi>Intolerable Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> and that all the uneaſie Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of this Life, are nothing to the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:36225:54"/>Heavenly Joys which the Almighty <hi>has prepared for thoſe that Love him.</hi> Did <hi>Eſau</hi> truly love himſelf, when <hi>for a Morſel of Meat</hi> he <hi>ſold his Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right?</hi> The preſent ſatisfaction of his Humour, was it not ſoon paſt? And did not he <hi>himſelf</hi> remain a ſtanding Monument of his own Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? Did he not Repent too late, and <hi>found no place of Repentance, tho' he ſought it with Tears?</hi> And was not he himſelf a ſufficient Witneſs of his being Fool enough to Love a trifle better than himſelf? Such Fools as this, and worſe, are all <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane</hi> Self-lovers. They Love their Humour, not themſelves; and to content ſome ſilly Humour, for a Moment, they are willing to deſtroy themſelves for ever. <hi>If any one will come after me,</hi> ſays our Saviour, <hi>let him deny himſelf, and follow me;</hi> let him deny his own unreaſonable Humour, and follow my Advice; let him follow me, who am the <hi>Way</hi> to <hi>Truth;</hi> let him follow me, who am that very <hi>Truth,</hi> which is
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:36225:55"/>the <hi>Way</hi> to Everlaſting <hi>Life;</hi> let him not Idolize a fooliſh Humour, and Love it better than himſelf; but let him kindly and wiſely deny his Humor for a time, that he may Save himſelf for all Eternity.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As there is nothing ſo Wiſe for our Selves, ſo there is nothing ſo <hi>Charitable</hi> to our Neighbour. A Man who believes God's Word, and relies upon his Promiſes, is happy in a comfortable <hi>Hope</hi> of Enjoying him for ever. The Pleaſures of Fleſh and Blood are too mean to content him; they are the ſame which Brutes enjoy, and therefore he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſes them. He glories in the Pledges of his Hope; his being Made to the <hi>Divine Image,</hi> his being Redeem'd by the <hi>Merits</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and being thus Entitled to <hi>Grace</hi> here, and <hi>Glory</hi> hereafter. Theſe are the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons why he juſtly Values himſelf. They are the Excellencies which he is in Love with whereſoe'er he meets them, and therefore Loves his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as he Loves himſelf. The beſt
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:36225:55"/>Chriſtian is always the beſt Friend. He is the trueſt Friend, not only to himſelf, but to his Neighbour. The World is ſtrangely miſtaken in the Notion of true Friendſhip, as well as in that of Self-love. We com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly think a Man Loves himſelf mightily, when he allows himſelf in all his Humours: But alas! He only Loves his Humour, and at the ſame time Hates himſelf. He does not ſee it, and may be will not believe it, till he's Damn'd for it: But then his Hatred ſhews it ſelf too late; he Hates and Curſes himſelf for ever. In the ſame manner, we take him to be our beſt and faithfuleſt Friend, who is always moſt ready to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with us, and take our part in all things. But this is a miſtake, as great as the other. If our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour's Humours are any way un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, a true Friend may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to moderate, but can never find in his Heart to approve them. Nay, tho' their Humours are Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, yet if they are not Expedient,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:36225:56"/>'tis an Argument of true kindneſs to deny one's Neighbour, in all thoſe Caſes, in which one would be glad to have ſo much Vertue as to deny one's ſelf. For my own part, if ever I have need of a Friend, I only wiſh and pray I may fall into the Hands of a good Chriſtian; a Friend of God's own Making, Chuſing and Appointing. Let him be only able to aſſiſt me, I am very ſure, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſtian he is, the better Friend he'll ſhew himſelf: He'll act by No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler and Diviner Principles, than all the Humane Ties of Gratitude and Kindneſs: And will be ſure to do a great deal more for God's ſake, than any Body elſe will ever do for mine. I grant there are but few of theſe; but the fewer there are, the more's the pity: And I am very much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid, 'tis partly our own fault, that the World is not good enough to have more of them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As there is nothing ſo Wiſe, and Charitable, ſo there is nothing ſo Perfectly and Univerſally <hi>Juſt,</hi> as
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:36225:56"/>
                  <hi>Chriſtian Prudence.</hi> Altho' it neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily preſuppoſes <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Hope,</hi> yet the chief ground of it is <hi>Charity,</hi> by which we Love God above all things, and look upon all things elſe as nothing in Compariſon of Him. A Man whoſe Mind and Heart are throughly Enlightned and Enflam'd with this Coeleſtial Love, <hi>lays up his Treaſure in Heaven,</hi> where <hi>his Heart is:</hi> He <hi>gives to God what's due to God,</hi> he <hi>Adores and Serves him only,</hi> he renders to him his whole Being, his Soul, his Heart, and all that is within him: He deſpiſes all the <hi>Treaſures upon Earth,</hi> where <hi>Moth and Ruſt do Corrupt, and Thieves break through and Steal:</hi> Eternity is his great Aim, and therefore he ſcorns to quarrel about any Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Concerns, but eaſily and readily makes even Reckonings with all the World, by <hi>giving to</hi> Caeſar <hi>what is due to</hi> Caeſar, and to his Friends and Neighbours <hi>what is due to</hi> all of them. We never are Unjuſt to <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> to a Friend or Neighbour, but
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:36225:57"/>when we are ſtrongly tempted to it by an eager deſire of ſomething or other relating to our Honour, Profit or Pleaſure: And theſe are the very things which a good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Undervalues and Deſpiſes. When our Saviour ſaid to the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees, Shew me the Tribute-Money;</hi> and when he askt them, <hi>Whoſe is this Image and Superſcription?</hi> He was not ignorant of either: But was willing to let them underſtand how little he valued theſe Money-mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which were the leaſt part of his Care. A <hi>Chriſtian</hi> is a Man of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World; and all the while he is in this, he chiefly minds his way to the next. He knows that his good Actions are the only things which have a Current Value there: And as for the Riches of this World, he does not covet to be loaded with them, but only to have a little about him, as much as may ſuffice to pay his ſhare by the way. He conſiders that the way is ſhort, and therefore is eaſily ſatisfied with any thing.
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:36225:57"/>If he Lodge uneaſily, and Fare a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle hardly in his Journey, 'tis only the common Fate of Travellers; he cheerfully makes the beſt of it; and comforts himſelf with thinking how plentifully he ſhall Feaſt for ever, when he comes to his Eternal Home.</p>
               <p>O <hi>God,</hi> who art the only <hi>Refuge</hi> of Sinners, the only <hi>Strength</hi> of the Weak, and only <hi>Author of all Piety,</hi> incline thy Ears of Pity and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion <hi>to the Pious Prayers of thy Church;</hi> forgive our paſt Offences, all our Folly, Malice, and Injuſtice; direct us in the ways of thy own Wiſdom, Charity and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and never ceaſe to aſſiſt us with thy Grace, that what by thy Encouragement we <hi>confidently ask,</hi> we may <hi>effectually obtain:</hi> Thro' Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="discourse">
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:36225:58"/>
            <head>Diſcourſe V. Of Chriſtian Humility.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>JEſus went into the Houſe of one of the Chief</hi> Phariſees <hi>to eat Bread, on the Sabbath-day, and they watched him. And behold there was a certain Man before him which had the Dropſie. And Jeſus anſwering, ſpake unto the Lawyers and Phariſees, ſaying, Is it Lawful to heal on the Sabbath-day? But they held their Peace. And he took him, and healed him, and let him go. And anſwer'd them, ſaying, Which of you ſhall have an Aſs or an Ox fallen into a Pit, and will not ſtraightway pull him out on the Sabbath-day? And they could not anſwer him to theſe things. And he told a Parable to thoſe who were In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited, obſerving how they choſe out the chief places, ſaying unto them, When thou art Invited to a Wedding, ſit not down in the higheſt place, leſt perhaps
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:36225:58"/>a more honourable Man than thou be Invited by him; and he, who Invited thee and him, come and ſay to thee: Give place to this Man; and then thou begin with ſhame to take the loweſt place. But when thou art Invited, go and ſit down in the loweſt place: That, when he comes who Invited thee, he may ſay unto thee: Friend, go up higher. Then ſhalt thou have honour in preſence of thoſe who ſit with thee. For whoſoever exalteth himſelf, ſhall be humbled; and he that humbleth himſelf, ſhall be exalted.</hi> Luk. 14. v. 1. <hi>to</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>This Goſpel preſents to our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration the Beſt of Moral Vertues, Humility; exerciſed by the Beſt of Mankind, Jeſus Chriſt, true God as well as Man; and deliver'd by the Beſt of Oracles, Truth it ſelf Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate. <hi>Learn of me,</hi> ſays he, <hi>becauſe I am humble of Heart.</hi> His whole Life was a conſtant Leſſon of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility. He taught it us, not only by word, but by example. And that we may the better learn our
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:36225:59"/>Leſſon, I ſhall endeavour to ſhew, according to the order of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; 1. How He <hi>Practiſed</hi> this great Vertue. 2. How he <hi>Preach'd</hi> it.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>'Tis the nature of <hi>Charity</hi> to make us <hi>Humble;</hi> and <hi>Humility</hi> is alſo a natural Diſpoſition towards being <hi>Charitable.</hi> If we conſider <hi>Charity</hi> in order to <hi>God,</hi> we plainly ſee that a Man, who truly <hi>Loves</hi> Him <hi>above all things,</hi> cannot but undervalue all the fading Glories of this World. The Gaudy Scene of all its Vanity makes little or no Impreſſion upon him: He eaſily diſcerns how falſe its Luſtre is: He ſees quite through it, and ſees Eternity beyond it. If we conſider the ſame <hi>Charity</hi> in order to our <hi>Neighbour,</hi> whom we Love for God's ſake, as being Made to the ſame Divine Image, Ranſom'd by the ſame Infinite <hi>Price,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Entitled to the ſame <hi>Grace</hi> here, as well as the ſame <hi>Eternal Glory</hi> hereafter: Theſe great and glorious
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:36225:59"/>Motives ſhine ſo bright, that all thoſe heaps of Honour which the World is able to Accumulate upon us, are no better than ſo many Dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hils in compariſon of theſe ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable Jewels. A Man, who chiefly Loves himſelf and his Neighbour upon theſe accounts, can have no longing paſſion for any preference on Earth: He cannot but diſdain all theſe inferiour Excellencies, Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Praiſes; becauſe the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his Mind and Heart is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely greater; and all theſe Trifles are as much below his Thoughts, as Heaven is above them.</p>
               <p>Thus we ſee how <hi>Charity</hi> inclines us to be <hi>Humble;</hi> and 'tis as eaſie to diſcover how <hi>Humility</hi> diſpoſes and prepares us to be <hi>Charitable.</hi> It removes the Obſtacles of <hi>Charity:</hi> It leſſens our inclinations to thoſe things which commonly create Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion amongſt us: In a word, it baniſhes that Pride, Ambition, and Vanity, which are the uſual ſubject of our Quarrels; and makes the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:36225:60"/>way plain and eaſie towards a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and a happy Union of Peace and Love. A Proud Man thinks it a leſſening of his Greatneſs, to make the leaſt ſtep towards any Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilement. He ſcorns to ſtoop to his Duty, but expects that every Body elſe ſhould bow to his Imperious Humour. On the contrary, an Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Man is aſham'd of being ſo Proud. If his Neighbour happens to be Captious, Envious or Malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, he freely forgives his fault, and pities his fall; and never thinks it below him, to go and ſeek him out, and even ſtoop to help him up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
               <p>We read in the beginning of this Goſpel, how <hi>Jeſus went into the Houſe of one of the chief Phariſees,</hi> that is to ſay, of his <hi>chief</hi> Enemies, <hi>to eat Bread.</hi> A Proud Man would have ſcorn'd to eat the Bread of an Enemy; but our Saviour's Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was too Charitable to need any Invitation, and his Charity too Humble to deſire it. There was
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:36225:60"/>good to be done; and that was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to Invite him. He knew very well their Pride and Malice: But at the ſame time he conſider'd, that the prouder they were, the more they wanted his aſſiſtance; and the more they wanted it, the more willing he was to afford it. He knew they would not come to him to fetch it: And therefore he <hi>went into the Houſe</hi> to bring it to them, and in a manner force it upon them.</p>
               <p>Behold the Example of our hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Redeemer! Are we always rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to follow it? Are we at all times willing to oblige our Enemies? Do not we take quite other Meaſures? If our Enemy diſdains to make the firſt Step towards us: If he expects that we begin to ſhew reſpect and kindneſs: If he takes upon him a great deal more than he deſerves: Do not we behave our ſelves as if we thought our ſelves obliged in Honour to be as Proud as he? Do not we ſometimes find a ſecret ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:36225:61"/>in ſhewing to the World, how high a Spirit we have? How hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily we deſpiſe all thoſe that ſlight us? And is it not a ſtrange Folly, to value ſo much that very Pride in our ſelves, which we deſpiſe ſo hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily in our Neighbours?</p>
               <p>Our Saviour knew very well the <hi>Phariſees</hi> were his Enemies; he knew they cared not for him; he knew they ſlighted him; and yet he freely goes <hi>into the Houſe,</hi> to ſeek their Company. He knew <hi>they</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways <hi>watched him,</hi> whereſoe're he went, and whatſoe're he did or ſaid. He knew <hi>they watched</hi> him, with a Spiteful and Malicious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, to Miſinterpret all his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, Words and Actions. He knew by Conſequence how little Probability there was of doing any Good amongſt them. But yet there was ſtill ſome little Appearance; and as long as there was any left, he could not forbear embracing any Opportunities of courting their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem, or gaining their good Will.
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:36225:61"/>Not that he either valued or wanted their Favour or Affection, but that he might teach them to value what they wanted themſelves; and that they might be ready and deſirous to receive, and to improve, thoſe truly Valuable Bleſſings, which his Hands were always full of.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And behold there was a certain Man before him, which had the Dropſie.</hi> 'Twas enough that the <hi>Man was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him:</hi> He could not behold his Miſery, without pitying it: He could not ſee his Want, without deſiring to Relieve it. But howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, becauſe he was ſurrounded by his Enemies, the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> who carefully obſerv'd, and <hi>watch'd him,</hi> with Deſign to make him Odious to the People: Therefore <hi>Jeſus an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering, ſpoke to the Lawyers, and the</hi> Phariſees, <hi>ſaying, Is it lawful to Heal on the Sabbath-Day?</hi> Our Pride would never have endured to ſhew ſo much Civility to thoſe who ſeek to undermine our Credit, and are not contented to Deſpiſe and
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:36225:62"/>Hate us, but are Studious and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious to make us Odious and Contemptible to every Body elſe. We think it below us to humour ſuch People; we look upon it as an Argument of a mean Spirit, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with them; we take a great deal of Pleaſure, in ſhewing how Great we are in our own Little Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, and how much we diſdain the very ſeeming to value thoſe who undervalue us. Our Saviour was humbler than we: He did not value the Opinion of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> but yet he was humble enough, to give them leave to think he did ſo. He knew, that the only way to do them Good, was firſt to pleaſe them: And that he could not pleaſe them better, than by ſeeming to conſult them. <hi>Is it Lawful,</hi> ſays he, <hi>to Heal on the Sabbath-Day?</hi> If he had gone to School to learn the Law of them, he could not have put the Queſtion in more Humble Terms; but yet <hi>they held their Peace.</hi> Their Pride would not ſuffer them
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:36225:62"/>to run the Hazard of expoſing their Ignorance, by reaſoning the Matter with him: They were Conſcious, that they had but little Reaſon on their ſide; but their Malice made them hope, that, in his Abſence, they might afterwards be able to find Fault with him, and colour their Detraction with ſuch Plauſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Pretences, as might make him paſs, in the Opinion of the People, for a Scandalous Perſon, who had little or no Regard to the Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of the <hi>Sabbath.</hi> Our Saviour knew their Malice, and ſaw their Pride: But, at the ſame time, knowing that their ſtubborn Silence might very civilly be taken for Conſent: And having ſhew'd his <hi>Humility,</hi> in referring himſelf to their Judgment, he reſolved to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer no longer his <hi>Charity</hi> to the Dropſical Man: <hi>He took him, and Heal'd him, and let him go.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This was not all. He was not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, that their Silence was enough to ſtop their Mouths, and to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:36225:63"/>them from blaming what they durſt not contradict. He did not conſider himſelf ſo much as them. He had done one Miracle already, but he had yet more Miracles to do: And not only more, but greater. He had cur'd one Body of a <hi>Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie;</hi> but what was that to ſo many Souls before him, which were all of them more Dropſical, and much more dangerouſly Sick? Alas, poor Creatures! They were puffed up with a great Exceſs of Pride: They were almoſt ready to burſt with Envious and Malicious Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and yet they thirſted eager<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for freſh Occaſions, to dilate theſe Humours, and encreaſe the Torment of their Minds. They ſaw the Swelling of the poor Man's Fleſh, but did not ſee the greater Swelling of their own proud Hearts. They pitied his Body, but were too blind to pity their own Souls.</p>
               <p>To tell them, in plain Terms, how Blind and Proud they were, would never do them any Good: It
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:36225:63"/>would neither Humble them, nor Open their Eyes: It would only ſerve to Aggravate their Pride, and Blind them ſo much more. When Pride is the Diſeaſe, Humility muſt be the Cure; and an Humble Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon muſt undertake it, or elſe 'twill never ſucceed. A Proud Man muſt be always treated gently, and gain'd by Inſenſible Degrees. To gain up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, we muſt not offer to At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack him, as if we deſign'd a Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry over him; neither muſt we di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly Contradict him. His Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ims indeed are often Contradicto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to one another: But the great Difficulty is, how to go about to make him ſee it. To take upon us to ſhew it plainly to him, is as great an Affront, as if we pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be clearer-ſighted than he. And therefore the beſt way is to lead him fairly and ſoftly by his own Principles, till we have brought him ſo near the Matter, that he may eaſily and clearly ſee his own Miſtake, without our pointing at it.
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:36225:64"/>Let him but have the Honour of ſeeming to find it himſelf, and then he'll willingly own it. To do all this is no hard Task, unleſs we are as Proud as he. If we are tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Humble, we ſhall take Delight in it. The Prouder he is, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is his Fall; and the Humbler we are, the Lower we ſhall willingly ſtoop to help him up again.</p>
               <p>We have already ſeen how Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble our Saviour was, in not offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Cure the Dropſical Man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he had Conſulted the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; and by their Silence, had a juſt Pretence to take it for granted, that the thing was fitting to be done. Let us now conſider, how Humbly he behaved himſelf after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, as ſoon as he had <hi>Heal'd</hi> the Man, and <hi>let him go.</hi> To let them ſee how far he was from Slighting or Deſpiſing their Opinion of him, he Appeals to their own Principles, and by a Familiar Example, lets them underſtand what Reaſon he had to judge, they could not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:36225:64"/>diſlike what he had done. <hi>Which of you,</hi> ſays he, <hi>ſhall have an Aſs or an Ox fallen into a Pit, and will not ſtraightway pull him out on the Sabbath-Day?</hi> A Proud Man would have gloried in being bold enough, to tell them to their Faces, how Blind, how Covetous, and how Uncharitable they were. Our Saviour teaches us another Leſſon: <hi>Learn of me, becauſe I am Humble.</hi> He does not tell them, they are Proud and Blind, but endeavours to put them in a way of Opening their Eyes, and chuſes that Method of diſcourſing, which was leaſt offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive to them. He does not tell them, they are Covetous, but ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues from a particular Maxim of their own, which he knew their Covetouſneſs would always help them to approve of.</p>
               <p>Their <hi>Vanity</hi> of being exact, in the Obſervance of the Sabbath, was greater than their <hi>Charity</hi> to their Neighbour: And therefore they concluded it was a Tranſgreſſion of
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:36225:65"/>the Law, to Cure a Man upon the Sabbath. But yet their <hi>Covetouſneſs</hi> was more Predominant than all their <hi>Vain Hypocriſie;</hi> and therefore, if any of their Goods were endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger'd upon the Sabbath, they did not doubt but it was Lawful to ſecure them. The Life of an Aſs or an Ox, provided it were their own, was a great deal more to them than the Life of a Neighbour. To ſave the Life of a Beaſt, which was worth Money to them, this was a thing of real Importance, which the Ceremonious Piety of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath might very well give Place to. But to ſave the Life of a Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, by whom, perhaps, they were not like to get a Penny, alas! What ſignified his Life to them? They were never like to be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for it: Let him e'en die, ſay they, and let us keep the Sabbath.</p>
               <p>Behold what Blindneſs we are capable of, when Pride and Paſſion over-rule our Reaſon! Let us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it well, and lay it ſeriouſly to
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:36225:65"/>Heart. Let it be a continual In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to us, which may daily Humble us, and make us always Jealous of our ſelves. We are made of the ſame Fleſh and Blood; we are liable to the ſame Pride and Paſſion; and may, for ought we know, be as Extravagantly, and as Proudly Blind, as they. The only way to Open our Eyes, and ſee that Pride which Blinds us, is to obſerve the Doctrine and Example of our Humble Saviour. He is <hi>the Light of the World:</hi> He <hi>Enlightens every Man that comes into it:</hi> He is the only <hi>Light,</hi> in which we can truly ſee, how Proud we are. And is it not a wonderful thing, that <hi>Light</hi> it ſelf ſhould ſhine ſo bright before the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> and they not ſee it? The Goſpel takes notice, that <hi>they could not anſwer him to theſe things:</hi> But however we do not read that they ſubmitted to him. Their Pride and Paſſion made them <hi>love Darkneſs ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than Light.</hi> And yet our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our took all Care imaginable, to
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:36225:66"/>make his Light acceptable and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to them, for fear, leſt they might ſhut their Eyes againſt it. <hi>Which of you ſhall have an Aſs or an Ox fallen into a Pit, and will not ſtraightway pull him out on the Sabbath-day?</hi> He only propoſes, with all Humility, a modeſt Queſtion, without the leaſt reflecting upon them; and leaves them to their own Diſcretion, to apply it to themſelves. My God! How profoundly Humble is thy In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite <hi>Charity!</hi> How infinitely Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable is thy Profound <hi>Humility!</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>If it be true, that <hi>Charity</hi> makes us <hi>Humble,</hi> 'tis no leſs certain, that <hi>Self-Love</hi> makes us <hi>Proud.</hi> When once we loſe the <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>God above all things,</hi> we turn our Back upon the Light; and being in the Dark, it is no wonder that we blindly doat upon our ſelves. We have loſt the Preſence of our God, whoſe Infinite Goodneſs was the Boundleſs Object of our Minds, and fill'd the utmoſt
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:36225:66"/>Stretch of our Unlimited Deſires: And, when we loſe him, 'tis no wonder if we find our Hearts as Empty as our God is Great. As he is infinitely Great, ſo we are infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely Empty without him: And all that we can find amongſt His Creatures is never Great enough to ſatisfie us. This is the Reaſon why we are ſo fond of Greatneſs. 'Tis the true Cauſe why we are ſo Proud, Ambitious, Vain, and Envious. All our Honours, Dignities and Praiſes, all our Actions and Pretentions, every thing belonging to us muſt be Great: And, if we cannot in our ſelves be Great, according to our Wiſhes, we make it out, with fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cying we are greater than our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. We ſtudy their Faults, and wink at our own; we ſtudy our own Advantages, and wink at theirs; we do what we can to leſſen them, and magnifie our ſelves; and all this Care is taken, only to purchaſe an Agreeable Miſtake of htinking we are greater than they.
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:36225:67"/>If this ſucceeds not, but, in ſpite of all Self-flattering Arts, we ſtill are Conſcious of our Neighbour's Merit being greater than ours; our laſt Refuge is to have Recourſe to the Opinion of others, to make Amends for what's deficient in our own. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we cannot deceive our ſelves, yet ſtill we hope that they may be deceiv'd in us, and think us Great, in ſpite of all our Littleneſs: And 'tis no matter how little we are at home, provided we are great abroad. If our Acquaintance Love us, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour us, and Praiſe us, more than any Body elſe; if they Extol us, Magnifie us, and Cry us up, above all others; we care not what Place we have in our own Thoughts, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided we have the firſt Place in theirs. The firſt Place is the thing we always aim at: We cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure that any Body elſe ſhould have it: And the more earneſtly we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to <hi>exalt</hi> our ſelves, the ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er we are <hi>humbled.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:36225:67"/>
               <p>The reaſon is plain. Becauſe our being thus exalted in the Minds and Hearts of other People, is a priviledge depending entirely upon their courteſie, and a favour not to be obtain'd by force or fear. Eſteem and Love are never to be had for asking; much leſs by laying claim to them, as if we thought them due to us. Mens Thoughts are their own; they are free to think what they pleaſe: And will ever do ſo, without craving our leave for it. They cannot love us, unleſs they like us: And how can they like us, if we take upon us to oblige them to it? 'Tis a viſible Encroachment up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the liberty of their Thoughts and Inclinations: A liberty which God himſelf allows them; and a liberty which all the United Strength of Mankind is not able to take from them. Let us do and ſay what we can, they are abſolute Maſters at home, and altogether Arbitrary in their own Dominions: We cannot chuſe our place in their Affection or
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:36225:68"/>Eſteem: And the only way to get the beſt preferment amongſt them, is to challenge none at all, but only endeavour to deſerve it, and always leave it to their own diſcretion. To do otherwiſe, will only ſerve to make us odious and ridiculous. And therefore our Saviour gives us warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not to chuſe <hi>the higheſt place,</hi> for fear leſt we <hi>begin with ſhame to take the loweſt:</hi> But, on the contrary, to <hi>go and ſit down in the loweſt place,</hi> that we may afterwards <hi>go higher,</hi> and <hi>have</hi> ſo much greater <hi>honour in preſence of thoſe who ſit with us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here I cannot but admire our Saviour's Charitable Condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to us, in making uſe of our own Principles to inſtruct us, and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying our Frailties, ſo as to make them ſerviceable to us. When Pride is predominant in us, we fear no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than being humbled, and hope for nothing more than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing exalted: Theſe are our greateſt hopes and fears: And, becauſe they are ſo, therefore our Saviour makes
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:36225:68"/>choice of them to Check the unruly motions of our Pride. What is it, but a violent deſire of being Exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that makes us ſo fierce in chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenging Reſpect, ſo loud in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of Neglect, ſo hot in quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling about it, ſo implacable in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting it, ſo furious and ſo cruel in revenging it? We think that by theſe means we may perhaps be able to force our way to Honour, and make a Conqueſt of <hi>the higheſt place</hi> in the Eſteem and Love of Men: But alas! We always find our ſelves moſt grievouſly miſtaken. Such means as theſe, if we are Rich and Powerful, may poſſibly prevail ſo far upon ſome few mean Spirits, as to make them fear and flatter us: But 'tis impoſſible, this way, to make them ever Love us, or Eſteem us. And ſince our ſtrongeſt hopes and fears are ſo much bent upon this ſilly Method of endeavouring to exalt our ſelves; what ſtronger Argument could be employed to Curb the impetuous Sallies of our
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:36225:69"/>Pride, than to open our Eyes, and let us plainly ſee, that whilſt we are thus haſtening to invade <hi>the higheſt place,</hi> we are continually poſting to <hi>the loweſt?</hi> Becauſe the prouder we ſeem to be, the more they hate us, and deſpiſe us. The more they hate the Injuſtice of our being ſo; and the more they deſpiſe the Folly of our ſhewing it.</p>
               <p>The Injuſtice of a Proud Self-lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is ſo Notorious, that nothing can excuſe or palliate it. If he could have it for asking, he would make no ſcruple to Monopolize the Eſteem and Love of all the World. 'Tis All too little for him, and therefore no ſhare of it can content him. If it lay in his power, he would humble every Body elſe, to make room for his own dear Self. He is unjuſt both to God and Man. He prefers him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf before both. And if this be not unjuſt, I know not what to call ſo. Our God who made us, is he not infinitely better than all his Creatures? And is it not juſt that
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:36225:69"/>we ſhould Love him beſt? Does not the <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>higheſt</hi> place, in all Mens Minds and Hearts, belong to him? How dare we then ſo inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently offer to pretend to it? Our Neighbours, are they not made by the ſame God, and for the ſame glorious End? Are they not all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited to the ſame Eternal Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? He who Invites us, is he not the ſame who Made us? He Made us what he pleas'd; and does it not therefore belong to him to Aſſign us what place he pleaſes? What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we <hi>are,</hi> whatever we <hi>have,</hi> whatever we <hi>imagine</hi> greater in our ſelves than others, we have no juſt reaſon to be Proud of it; becauſe 'tis no Property of our own, but a free Gift of our Maſter, without our firſt deſerving it. We may be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly thankful for it, but have no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to glory in it; becauſe it does not argue that we are better than others, but only that God is better and kinder to us than he is to them. We did not <hi>Make</hi> our ſelves, we did
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:36225:70"/>not <hi>Invite</hi> our ſelves, and therefore muſt not <hi>Chuſe</hi> for our ſelves. We have no Right to our being <hi>Made,</hi> no Claim to our being <hi>Invited,</hi> no Title of our own to any <hi>Place</hi> at all: And ſince there's <hi>no Place</hi> due to us, Are we not horribly Unjuſt, if nothing but <hi>the higheſt Place</hi> will ſatisfie us?</p>
               <p>In a word, there's nothing ſo Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt and Odious, nothing ſo Unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and Ridiculous, as Pride. And therefore 'tis no wonder if the higher we Aim, the lower we fall. No wonder, I ſay, if it be always true, that <hi>Whoſoever Exalts himſelf, ſhall</hi> certainly <hi>be Humbled,</hi> by <hi>Men,</hi> in this World, and by <hi>the Devil and his Angels,</hi> in the next.</p>
               <p>On the other ſide, there's nothing ſo Humble, nothing ſo Divine, as Charity; and, at the ſame time, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the World ſo Charitable, ſo truly Great and Generous, as true Humility. And therefore 'tis no wonder that our Saviour aſſures us, <hi>He that Humbles himſelf, ſhall be Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted.</hi>
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:36225:70"/>If he <hi>Humbles</hi> himſelf exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riourly in the ſight of Men, he will be ſure to be <hi>Exalted,</hi> Lov'd, and Honour'd by them <hi>here.</hi> And if he <hi>Humbles</hi> himſelf ſincerely in the ſight of God, he cannot fail to be <hi>Exalted</hi> Everlaſtingly <hi>hereafter.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="discourse">
               <head>Diſcourſe VI. Of Chriſtian Marriage, and the Means to Sanctifie it.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THere was a Marriage in</hi> Cana <hi>of</hi> Galilee, <hi>and the Mother of Jeſus was there. And Jeſus alſo was invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and his Diſciples, to the Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age. And when they wanted Wine, the Mother of Jeſus ſaith unto him, They have no Wine. And Jeſus ſaith unto her, Woman, what's that to me and thee? My Hour is not yet come. His Mother ſaith unto the Servants, Whatſoever he ſaith unto you, do it. Now there were ſet there Six Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pots
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:36225:71"/>of Stone, after the manner of the Purifying of the</hi> Jews, <hi>containing Two or Three Meaſures apiece. Jeſus ſaith unto them, Fill the Water-pots with Water. And they filled them up to the Brim. And he ſaith unto them, Draw out now, and preſent</hi> it <hi>to the Governour of the Feaſt. And they preſented</hi> it. <hi>But when the Ruler of the Feaſt had taſted the Water that was made Wine, and knew not whence it was, (but the Servants which drew the Water, knew) the Governour of the Feaſt called the Bridegroom, and ſaith unto him, Every Man at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning doth ſet forth good Wine, and when Men have well drunk, then that which is worſe; but thou haſt kept the good Wine until now. This beginning of Miracles did Jeſus in</hi> Cana <hi>of</hi> Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilee, <hi>and manifeſted his Glory; and his Diſciples believed in him.</hi> John 2. v. 1, to 12.</p>
               <p>This Goſpel affords great Comfort and Inſtruction, not only to thoſe who engage themſelves in Marriage, but alſo to all Chriſtians whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:36225:71"/>even thoſe who lead a ſingle Life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>The firſt thing we read in the Goſpel is, that <hi>there was a Marriage, and the Mother of Jeſus was there;</hi> and not the <hi>Mother</hi> only, but <hi>Jeſus alſo was</hi> himſelf <hi>invited</hi> to it. They were both <hi>invited,</hi> and were both of them pleaſed to be <hi>there.</hi> They were not contented to come them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to honour this Happy Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; but, the <hi>Diſciples</hi> being alſo invited for their Maſter's ſake, He was pleas'd to bring them with him, that they might be Witneſſes, how much he honour'd it, and that his Apoſtles afterwards might preach with greater Aſſurance this Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Doctrine, that <hi>Marriage</hi> is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways <hi>Honourable,</hi> not only in it ſelf, but <hi>in all</hi> who rightly engage in it, and obſerve the Duties of it.</p>
               <p>There's nothing raiſes more the Value of any Commendation, than to have it given by thoſe who are
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:36225:72"/>Commendable for being of a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Profeſſion. Such a Commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion carries with it a much fairer ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of being Impartial and Sincere, and therefore is more juſtly Valuable.</p>
               <p>If Marriage were eſteem'd and praiſed only by married People, we ſhould not much admire the Commendations which they ſo frankly beſtow upon their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. But when we ſee Virginity it ſelf do ſo much Juſtice to a Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Life, as to approve it: When we ſee the two moſt perfect Patterns of Virginity, the Virgin Son of God, and Virgin Mother, Vouchſafe to Adorn a Wedding with the Glory of their Preſence: When we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that although they both of them preferr'd a Virgin Life ſo much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it, that the one would not be Born of a Woman unleſs ſhe were a Virgin, neither was the other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to be his Mother, till ſhe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, that by a Miracle ſhe might be Fruitful without the leaſt Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:36225:72"/>of her Virginity; yet neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, they both of them were pleaſed to Accept the Invitation, and be Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of the Solemnity: When, I ſay, we duly conſider all theſe Circumſtances, we muſt needs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that although <hi>Virginity</hi> be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferrable as being more perfect, yet the <hi>State</hi> of <hi>Marriage</hi> is truly <hi>Honourable</hi> in it ſelf, and ought to be honour'd by all Mankind, ſince God himſelf was pleas'd to Honour it.</p>
               <p>Chriſtian Marriage is the Nurſery of Chriſtianity, the School where Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren learn the Rudiments of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Vertue, and the Academy where they are daily Train'd up to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of it. <hi>Let the Little ones come to me,</hi> ſays <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the Goſpel: And 'tis the great Duty of Parents to bring their little ones to him. The In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Chriſtian Marriage, aims at no leſs Glorious an End, than that for which the Son of God was pleaſed to come into the World; which is, that the Children of Men may, by his Grace, <hi>become</hi> the <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:36225:73"/>of God.</hi> For this Reaſon he Eſtabliſh'd his <hi>Holy Church</hi> upon Earth; He gave <hi>Apoſtles, Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>Paſtors,</hi> to carry on <hi>the Work of the Miniſtry;</hi> and gave a ſtrict Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to Parents to bring their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to him, that they may <hi>know</hi> his Holy Will, and <hi>do</hi> it, that they may <hi>grow up in him in all things,</hi> and that by daily Improvement in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of all Chriſtian Duties, they may repleniſh the Church Militant <hi>here,</hi> and the Church Triumphant <hi>here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. If any,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>have not Care of their own,</hi> and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of thoſe who are <hi>of their own Houſe,</hi> their own Family, their own Fleſh and Blood, <hi>they have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the Faith, and are worſe than Infidels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I muſt confeſs, 'tis no ſmall Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour for Married Perſons to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Coadjutors of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in that great Work which brought him down from Heaven: But then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, I cannot deny but that this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Honour brings along with it ſo
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:36225:73"/>many and ſuch heavy Obligations, that unleſs the Grace of God ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port them, it will only ſerve to cruſh them with its Weight. A Virgin has only one <hi>Soul</hi> to ſave, one <hi>Perſon</hi> to pleaſe, one <hi>Paſſion</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer. This <hi>Paſſion,</hi> being taken young, is eaſily made tame; and, being uſed to that Subjection which it owes to Reaſon, grows contented with it. This <hi>Perſon</hi> is its own dear Self; one Mind, one Humour with it ſelf; and is not eaſily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd with to diſpleaſe it ſelf. This <hi>Soul</hi> is entirely its own; it is not divided betwixt a Neighbour and it ſelf; 'tis the whole Object of its great Concern, the only Neceſſary one; and being free from all Diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, it has nothing elſe to do, but to endeavour the Salvation of it ſelf. But it is not ſo with Married People. They muſt take great Care to ſave their Children's Souls, or elſe they greatly endanger their own. They muſt inſtruct them in all their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; and that's ſome little Trouble.
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:36225:74"/>They muſt, in all things, give them good Example; and that's a great deal more Troubleſome. They muſt bear patiently whatever Croſſes they meet with from their Children; and this is not always eaſie. They muſt be as patient, and more, if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, in bearing with all the Faults and Humours of thoſe whom they have taken <hi>for better or worſe;</hi> and how hard this is, they only know who have tried it. On the one ſide, I do not eaſily conceive how Married People can pleaſe themſelves, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out pleaſing one another: And on the other ſide, I am very much afraid it is as difficult a thing to pleaſe two Perſons, as it is to ſerve two Maſters. I know very well, that according to the Inſtitution of Marriage, Man and Wife are but <hi>one.</hi> They are <hi>one</hi> in Law; they ought to be <hi>one</hi> in Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and Affection; and whilſt they are ſo, they are as happy as Marriage can make them: But when they are <hi>two,</hi> they are the worſt <hi>two</hi> in the World. There's nothing ſo
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:36225:74"/>ſoure as Love when it turns. From an Exceſſive Fondneſs, which created a Thouſand Extravagant Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and a Thouſand more Unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Jealouſies, they often paſs to to the other Extreme of hating more than ever they lov'd: And 'tis hard to ſay, which is the greater Plague of Marriage; too much Love, or too little. A Medium betwixt both is certainly the beſt: And even then there's enough to be done, and a great deal more to be ſuffer'd. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batements of Humour muſt be made, on the one ſide as well as the other; there muſt be mutual Condeſcenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons uſed; they muſt have Patience, if not always, at leaſt by turns: And all this little enough to maintain that Peace at home, and Credit abroad, without both which they cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to be eaſie. For want of this, we ſee the Ruin of many Families, who are a grievous Scandal to their own Domeſticks whilſt they live together, and a greater to the whole World when they part. To pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:36225:75"/>all theſe Diſorders, and to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern all their Paſſions with that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and Diſcretion which is neceſſary for their preſent Happineſs, and for the future Welfare of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and Children, both in this World and the next, the Grace of God is indiſpenſibly required. Their Frailty and Temptations are greater than ordinary, and therefore their Grace muſt be ſo too. They are as Frail and Weak as Water: And no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a Miracle of Grace can change their Water into Wine. This is that Comfortable <hi>beginning of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles</hi> which <hi>Jeſus did in</hi> Cana <hi>of Galilee,</hi> to <hi>Manifeſt his Glory,</hi> that all Married Chriſtians may be true <hi>Diſciples</hi> of him, and firmly <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in him,</hi> that though without him they are never able to Support the Difficulties of their State, yet by his <hi>Preſence</hi> and <hi>Aſſiſtance</hi> they may make thoſe Duties eaſie, which are otherwiſe impoſſible.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:36225:75"/>
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>'Tis a great Comfort to Married People, that the State wherein they engage is truly Honourable; and that God himſelf, his Virgin-Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and Diſciples, were pleas'd to Honour it with their <hi>Preſence.</hi> 'Tis yet a greater Comfort to Conſider, that <hi>the things which are Impoſſible with Men, are Poſſible with God;</hi> and that although ſometimes it may be morally Impoſſible for Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to endure with Patience the Cares and Croſſes which attend a Fooliſh or Unwary Choice, yet ſtill God's Mercy is ſo great, that he will rather Work a <hi>Miracle</hi> in Favour of them, than ſuffer his Omnipotent <hi>Aſſiſtance</hi> to be wanting to them. But though theſe Comforts are Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to Married Perſons, yet the Inſtructions of the Goſpel are more general, and may regard all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians whatſoever; not only thoſe who are Married, but even thoſe who lead a ſingle Life.</p>
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:36225:76"/>
               <p n="1">I. <hi>There was a Marriage,</hi> ſays the Evangeliſt, <hi>and Jeſus was invited.</hi> Without this Invitation, He would not have been preſent: And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his <hi>Preſence,</hi> they would have been deprived of his <hi>Aſſiſtance.</hi> This is the Caſe; not only of Marriage, but of any other Calling or Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion whatſoever. No good Chriſtian dares preſume, in any State of Life, to expect the Bleſſing of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out inviting him to give it. He muſt be <hi>preſent</hi> in their <hi>Hearts,</hi> by a Sincere Deſire of ſerving him, and ſaving their Souls. Whatever they engage in, they may perhaps have other Honeſt Motives, but this muſt always be the Chief. He muſt be alſo <hi>preſent</hi> in their <hi>Minds,</hi> by a Sincere Enquiry into his Holy Will and Pleaſure, which they conſult in every Deliberate Action, and much more in any Solemn Undertaking, which is like to have a greater and more laſting Influence upon their Lives. They <hi>invite</hi> not only <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> but <hi>his Diſciples</hi> alſo; when in
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:36225:76"/>all things they conſult thoſe Holy Maxims which He and his Apoſtles preach'd; and under the ſecure di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Faith, Hope, and Charity they fix their ſteady Eye upon the Glories of another Life, and Value this no farther than it is Subſervient to that. 'Tis thus they prove them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be true <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Deſcription, by <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying</hi> all <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodlineſs and Worldly Luſts,</hi> by living <hi>Soberly and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in this preſent World,</hi> and by <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting the Glorious Appearance of</hi> him, who is <hi>their God and Saviour, Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> 'Tis thus they ſhew to all the World the Sanctity of their Calling, and make it appear, as the Apoſtle ſays, that <hi>God has not call'd</hi> them <hi>to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, but to Holineſs,</hi> that <hi>every one may know how to Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs their Veſſel in Sanctification and Honour, and not in the Luſt of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence, like the Heathens, who know not God,</hi> and therefore know no Rule but their unruly Appetites. 'Tis thus they Build their whole
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:36225:77"/>Morality upon a true Chriſtian Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation: They <hi>believe,</hi> they <hi>hope,</hi> they <hi>love above all things,</hi> that Bleſt Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, whoſe <hi>Joys are ſet before them;</hi> and therefore take no Meaſures but what are ſuitable to it, and are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways <hi>Prudent</hi> in chuſing, <hi>Patient</hi> in ſuffering, <hi>Juſt</hi> and <hi>Temperate</hi> in all their doings.</p>
               <p>Even thoſe who differ from us in Matters of <hi>Faith,</hi> are (ſome of them) of the ſame Opinion with us in theſe Important Maxims of <hi>Morality.</hi> 
                  <q>A very Abſtemious Life, if it be not required as an Eſſential Part of Holineſs, yet it is neceſſary as the Means and Inſtrument of it: Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formably to that of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1. Cor. ch. 7. <hi>Brethren, the time is ſhort; it remaineth that they who have Wives, be as though they had none; and they that Rejoice, as though they rejoiced not; for the Figure of this World paſſes away.</hi> Where we are not only Interdicted unlawful Pleaſures, but forbidden to give our ſelyes up to lawful ones; and
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:36225:77"/>commanded to uſe ſuch <hi>Moderation</hi> as may become Men fully perſwaded of the <hi>Shortneſs</hi> and <hi>Vanity</hi> of this Life, and poſſeſſed by the Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a better. The Chriſtian State is a State of Holineſs and Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: 'Tis in one Word, to be <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly-minded:</hi> And therefore that Courſe of Liſe, which can beſt ſerve to Encreaſe this Bleſſed Temper, is the Chriſtian's Duty; and that which Softens and Senſualizes us, is Inconſiſtent with Chriſtianity. The great End of <hi>Temperance,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> ch. 9. is the <hi>Maſtery,</hi> or Conqueſt, over the World and Fleſh, whoſe Luſts and Pleaſures War againſt the Soul. Religion being nothing but the Love of God, and Heavenly things, the Goſpel endeavours all it can to wean us from the World and Fleſh; it being Impoſſible to ſerve Two ſuch contrary Intereſts. And, when the Soul is <hi>ſtriving</hi> for the <hi>Maſtery,</hi> is it Senſe to Arm the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, and Feed it into a Fierce and
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:36225:78"/>Brutiſh Courage, by indulging thoſe Enjoyments which are the Food and Fuel to its Luſts? In plainer Words: that Abſtinence from Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual Pleaſures, which renders the Body Governable and Serviceable to the Soul, which Frees the Mind from its Captivity to Sence, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhes its Dominion over the Brutiſh Part, is that <hi>Temperance</hi> which the Goſpel requires: And by Conſequence, that Indulgence to Worldly Pleaſures, which tends to Pamper and Enrage the Body, to awaken our Paſſions for this preſent State, to make the Minds of Men Soft and Feeble, Heavy and Senſual, unable to Suffer, and froward if their Appetite be not ſatisfied, is flatly Contradictory to the <hi>Temperance</hi> of the Goſpel of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. To obtain this <hi>Temperance,</hi> this <hi>Maſtery</hi> over our ſelves, we muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve another great Inſtruction of our preſent Goſpel. We muſt not rely upon the length or number of
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:36225:78"/>our Prayers; we muſt <hi>Pray</hi> much, and <hi>Labour</hi> a great deal more; we muſt <hi>Pray</hi> ſometimes, and <hi>Labour</hi> always; our <hi>Praying</hi> is only <hi>part</hi> of our Duty, the <hi>whole</hi> of it chiefly conſiſts in <hi>doing</hi> all we can to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form it. Although we Pray for our ſelves, although the whole Church offers up her Prayers for us, although not only the Saints on Earth, but all the Saints in Heaven, join their Humble Supplications with ours, all this will never prevail, unleſs we add our own Endeavours, and <hi>do</hi> whatever we are able to the utmoſt of our Power. We read in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, <hi>when they wanted Wine, the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Jeſus ſaith unto him, They have no Wine.</hi> She Intercedes not with the <hi>Authority</hi> of a <hi>Mother,</hi> but with the <hi>Humility</hi> and <hi>Lowlineſs</hi> of a <hi>Handmaid.</hi> She barely Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends their <hi>Want,</hi> with that Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity, and Modeſty, and Loving Confidence, which even we Sinners may preſume to Imitate. Our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's anſwer ſeems a little Surpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:36225:79"/>
                  <hi>Woman, what's that to me and thee?</hi> He does not ſo much as call her <hi>Mother:</hi> He ſeems to Check the forwardneſs of her Submiſſive Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, by telling her, his <hi>Hour was not yet come.</hi> But at the ſame time he deſigned to do as ſhe deſir'd: And knew very well, that although the <hi>Hour</hi> was <hi>not yet come,</hi> it was not very far off. Her Humble Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er was a great Step towards it: And when the Servants had done their Duty, in following her directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and <hi>doing whatſoever</hi> Jeſus <hi>ſaid unto them,</hi> when they had <hi>fill'd the Water-pots with Water,</hi> and <hi>fill'd them up to the Brim,</hi> when they had done what they were bid to do, and whatſoever they were able, when they could not now do more than they had done already, then the <hi>Hour</hi> was <hi>come</hi> for <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf to do the reſt. <hi>Deaw now,</hi> ſays he, <hi>and preſent it:</hi> And then it was that all the Company were Witneſſes, the <hi>Hour</hi> appointed for the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle was <hi>come,</hi> when they plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:36225:79"/>
                  <hi>Taſted</hi> that <hi>the Water was made Wine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If we apply this duly to our ſelves, the Application will be very In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive. The <hi>Church</hi> of God, who is our common <hi>Mother,</hi> and is <hi>to us</hi> the <hi>Mother</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by <hi>forming</hi> his Spirit <hi>in us,</hi> is very ſenſible of our <hi>Want,</hi> and daily Recommends us, in her <hi>Prayers</hi> to <hi>Chriſt</hi> the <hi>Saviour of his Body,</hi> that our decaying Fervour may revive again, and our Devotion, which is grown quite Pall'd and Dead, may be Inſpired and Anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with new Life and Vigour. She Prays here upon Earth: She Prays in Heaven alſo, where her better part is now Triumphant, Secure of their own Happineſs, and only Solicitous for ours: And ſurely if <hi>the</hi> Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent <hi>Prayer of</hi> one <hi>Righteous Man,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſays, avails ſo <hi>much,</hi> the Prayers of ſo many Saints, both here and there, muſt needs be very Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent. But yet we muſt not lay more ſtreſs upon the Matter than 'tis able to bear. Their <hi>Praying</hi> as
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:36225:80"/>much as we pleaſe, will never ſerve our turn, without our <hi>doing</hi> as much as we can. This we can all of us do: And more than this, we are none of us obliged to: But this, at leaſt, we muſt always <hi>do,</hi> or elſe all <hi>Praying</hi> is in Vain.</p>
               <p>When we <hi>fall</hi> into Sin, we feel our Weakneſs: And when we <hi>ſtrive</hi> to <hi>riſe,</hi> we feel it more. We there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Pray to God to help us: The <hi>Church</hi> Prays for us too: But all this while we do not ſufficiently conſider that it is not in the Power of God himſelf to help us, unleſs we help our ſelves. To help us, is not to do the Work <hi>for</hi> us, but to do it <hi>with</hi> us. And then it is that the Almighty helps us, when we do thoſe Duties with him, which we cannot do without him. <hi>Repentance</hi> and <hi>Amendment</hi> are things which are not to be done by Proxy: Another's <hi>Repenting</hi> does not change our Hearts; another's <hi>Mending</hi> does not make us better: Such things as theſe are Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal, which we our ſelves muſt do,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:36225:80"/>or elſe we muſt <hi>All Periſh:</hi> And hence it follows clearly, that unleſs we help our ſelves, it is impoſſible for God to help us. How unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable therefore is the common Practice of thoſe People, who take great Care to <hi>ask</hi> God's help, and take no Care to <hi>have</hi> it? They <hi>Pray</hi> all; and <hi>do</hi> nothing. When they have done their <hi>Prayers,</hi> they think they have no more to <hi>do.</hi> They <hi>Pray</hi> indeed, that they may Seriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Heartily begin a thorough Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of their Lives, but ſtill they let their Duty take its Fortune, without ever <hi>beginn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>g</hi> to <hi>go about it</hi> in good earneſt.</p>
               <p>'Tis very obſervable in our preſent Goſpel, that, in order to the Miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Change of Water into Wine, there was more <hi>done</hi> than <hi>ſaid.</hi> The Mother of Jeſus <hi>ſaid</hi> only <hi>three</hi> or <hi>four</hi> Words to him: But there was a great deal more to be <hi>done.</hi> There were no leſs than <hi>Six</hi> Water-pots to be fill'd, and great ones too, ſuch as were then in uſe for the Waſhing
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:36225:81"/>or <hi>Purifying of the Jews:</hi> Our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our kindly deſigning to Work a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial Miracle, which might not only be a Relief of their Poverty at preſent, but a Proviſion againſt it for the Future. 'Tis alſo worth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving, that the Virgin-Mother's <hi>Exhortation</hi> to the <hi>Servants,</hi> was more ample, and more earneſt, than her <hi>Prayer</hi> to her <hi>Son;</hi> becauſe She knew very well her Petition would never be granted, unleſs the <hi>Servants</hi> took great Care to <hi>do whatſoever</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus <hi>ſaid unto them.</hi> Neither is it leſs Remarkable, that he no ſooner <hi>ſaid unto them, Fill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> be Water-pots with Water,</hi> but they immediately o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey'd, <hi>and fill'd them up to the Brim;</hi> and in the very Moment of their <hi>doing ſo,</hi> the Miracle was done, the <hi>Water was made Wine.</hi> If <hi>Chriſt</hi> had order'd them to fill the Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pots with <hi>Wine,</hi> they might have juſtly pleaded, it was more than than they could <hi>do:</hi> But ſince he only commanded them to fill them up with <hi>Water,</hi> they had no Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:36225:81"/>left; the Water was near at Hand, they might eaſily have it for fetching, and a little Labour was enough to do the Work. This puts me in Mind of a Celebrated Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of S. <hi>Auſtin, God does not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand impoſſible things, but by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding gives us warning to do what we can, and to ask what we cannot.</hi> Let us only <hi>do what we can,</hi> and <hi>what we cannot</hi> we are ſure to <hi>have</hi> for <hi>asking.</hi> We are ſure, I ſay, to have it granted in Proportion to what we <hi>do,</hi> and may be, in a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Meaſure than we <hi>ask.</hi> If we conſider well the Matter of <hi>Fact,</hi> we ſhall find the <hi>Quantity</hi> of Wine was <hi>more</hi> than any Body <hi>ask'd,</hi> but neither one Drop more nor leſs than what the Servants <hi>did</hi> in <hi>Drawing Water</hi> and <hi>Filling.</hi> Had the <hi>Water</hi> been <hi>leſs,</hi> the <hi>Wine</hi> had been <hi>ſo</hi> too: And had they Drawn <hi>no Water,</hi> they would have had <hi>no Wine</hi> at all.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Wine</hi> I ſpeak of, is the <hi>Wine</hi> of <hi>Grace:</hi> That <hi>Wine</hi> which Inebri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates the Soul with all Celeſtial De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:36225:82"/>and makes it ſo <hi>Heavenly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded,</hi> that it Loaths and Hates the Intoxicating Wine of Worldly Pleaſures: That Noble, Generous, and All-victorious <hi>Grace,</hi> which gives us the <hi>Maſtery</hi> we <hi>ſtrive for,</hi> but never-gives it without our <hi>ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving for it.</hi> This <hi>Grace</hi> is never granted to the Lazy and Idle Prayers of a Careleſs Sinner, nor ever denied to the Faithful and Vigorous Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of an Humble Penitent. A Penitent who labours all he can to <hi>Humble</hi> himſelf, and lays aſide all Cenſuring of his Neigbours, that he may the more effectually call home his Serious Thoughts, to Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and Correct himſelf: Who ſpares no Pains to <hi>do</hi> or <hi>ſuffer</hi> any thing that may be requiſite or uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to reform his Life: Who fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently and ſeriouſly Reflects upon the Vanity and Emptineſs of all Worldly Enjoyments, the Folly and Miſchief of doating upon them, the great Advantages and Pleaſures of deſpiſing them, and being thus
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:36225:82"/>deliver'd from the Tyranny and Slavery of all his Arbitrary, Reſtleſs and Inſatiable Paſſions: A Penitent, who uſes all his Art and Induſtry to ſet his Heart at Liberty, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver leaves off Cuarrelling with this unconſtant, ſilly, miſerable World, till he is quite fall'n out with it, and Hates the very Thought of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reconcil'd: A Penitent, I ſay, who will not endure to hear of any Treaty with his Enemies, the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil, but know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well their Treachery, does what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he can, 1. To avoid all thoſe Occaſions in which they ſeek to Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> him, 2. To cut off all Proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Succours which may Feed and Reinforce them, 3. To watch their Motions with ſuch Care, that not a ſingle Thought, Imagination, or Delight, can ever advance one ſtep beyond the Lines of their Duty, without being preſently obſerved, and vigorouſly repuls'd: Such a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent as this will certainly ſucceed, and gain the <hi>Grace</hi> he <hi>ſtrives for.</hi>
                  <pb n="162" facs="tcp:36225:83"/>'Tis true, the Endeavours of a Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent who has been long a Sinner, are as <hi>Weak</hi> as <hi>Water.</hi> But never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, if to the utmoſt of his Power he ſtruggles with himſelf, to <hi>do</hi> all thoſe things <hi>whatſoever Jeſus ſays unto him,</hi> he will ſoon, by joyful Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, find the <hi>Weakneſs</hi> of his <hi>Water</hi> chang'd into the <hi>Strength</hi> of <hi>Wine.</hi> Let him but <hi>fill up</hi> his beſt Endeavours <hi>to the Brim</hi> of his Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, (<hi>this</hi> he can always <hi>do,</hi> and God requires no more) let him <hi>do</hi> but <hi>this,</hi> and he will ſoon be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd, that Miracles are not ceas'd. The World indeed may wonder at his change of Life, and ſo did <hi>the Ruler of the Feaſt,</hi> when <hi>he Taſted the Water that was made Wine;</hi> he wonder'd, becauſe <hi>he knew not whence it was:</hi> But <hi>the Servants, which drew the Water, knew:</hi> And all God's <hi>Servants,</hi> who have been Sinners heretofore, <hi>know</hi> very well from whence their Change proceeds: They <hi>know</hi> 'tis from <hi>the Right Hand of the Higheſt;</hi> who will not let us loſe the
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:36225:83"/>every leaſt part of our Labour, but for little Drop of <hi>Water,</hi> gives us in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change an equal Share of <hi>Wine;</hi> and and in Requital of our Weak (but Conſtant and Sincere) Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, never fails to <hi>Aſſiſt</hi> our Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with a Proportionable <hi>Grace,</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> it with Eternal <hi>Glory.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="discourse">
            <head>Diſcourſe VII. Of True Repentance.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>IN the Fifteenth Year of the Reign of</hi> Tiberius Caeſar, Pontius Pilate <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Governor of</hi> Judea, <hi>and</hi> Herod <hi>being Tetrarch of</hi> Galilee, <hi>and his Brother</hi> Philip <hi>Tetrarch of</hi> Iturea, <hi>and of the Reign of</hi> Trachonitis <hi>and</hi> Lyſanias <hi>the Tetrarch of</hi> Abilene, Annas <hi>and</hi> Caiphas <hi>being the High Prieſts, the Word of God came unto</hi> John <hi>the Son of</hi> Zacharias <hi>in the Wilderneſs. And he came into all the Country about</hi> Jor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:36225:84"/>
               <hi>Preaching the Baptiſm of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, for the Remiſſion of Sins; as it is Written in the Book of the Words of</hi> Iſaias <hi>the Prophet: A Voice of one crying in the Wilderneſs; prepare the Way of the Lord, make his Paths Straight; every Valley ſhall be Fill'd; and every Mountain and Hill ſhall be brought Low; and the Crooked Ways ſhall be made Straight, and the Rough ones ſhall be made Smooth; and all Fleſh ſhall ſee the Salvation of God.</hi> Luke. 3. v. 1, to 7.</p>
            <p>We are All Sinners. We are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore All of us Highly concern'd in the Subject of this Goſpel. There's no <hi>Salvation</hi> to be had without <hi>Remiſſion</hi> of <hi>Sin:</hi> And no <hi>Remiſſion</hi> to hoped for, without True <hi>Repentance.</hi> For this Reaſon, <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> was call'd by God himſelf, and ſent to Preach it. <hi>The Word of God came to</hi> him <hi>in the Wilderneſs;</hi> and he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately obey'd: <hi>He came into all the Country about</hi> Jordan, <hi>Preaching Repentance for the Remiſſion of Sins.</hi> The Evangeliſt not only tells us the
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:36225:84"/>Deſign, and the Authority, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the Time of his Miſſion: And ſeems, by Marking the many Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of it, to be more careful in Dating the <hi>coming</hi> of S. <hi>John,</hi> than of our <hi>Lord</hi> himſelf; becauſe, unleſs by true <hi>Repentance</hi> we <hi>prepare the Way,</hi> his <hi>coming</hi> will be no Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to us, but only riſe in Judgment againſt us. To <hi>prepare the Way of our Lord,</hi> three things are neceſſary to be done. We muſt make it <hi>Level, Straight, and Smooth.</hi> And here I will not diſpute what difference there is, betwixt <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> and <hi>Doing Penance;</hi> becauſe, if we believe the <hi>Evangeliſt,</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> and the <hi>Voice of one cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Wilderneſs;</hi> if, I ſay, we believe the <hi>Word of God,</hi> by whom they were all Inſpired, we cannot doubt, but that <hi>Repentance,</hi> if True and Sincere, has a great deal to <hi>do;</hi> the <hi>doing</hi> of which is very Difficult and Mortifying, and therefore very well deſerves the Name of <hi>Doing Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</hi> 1. <hi>Every Mountain</hi> muſt <hi>be
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:36225:85"/>brought Low.</hi> 2. <hi>Every Crooked Way</hi> muſt <hi>be made Straight.</hi> 3. Every <hi>Rough Way</hi> muſt <hi>be made Smooth.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Every Mountain</hi> muſt <hi>be brought Low;</hi> and therefore our <hi>Proud Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption</hi> muſt be <hi>Humbled.</hi> We muſt neither be ſo <hi>Proud</hi> of our own Natural <hi>Strength,</hi> as to think we are able to ſave our Souls without God's helping us; neither muſt we <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume</hi> ſo much upon God's <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> as to expect that he ſhould ſave us, without our helping our ſelves.</p>
               <p>There are ſome People in the World, who have ſo great an Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of their Natural Strength, as to Imagine they can <hi>take Heaven by</hi> their own <hi>Force,</hi> and Storm it when they pleaſe: And therefore they do not apprehend the Danger of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing in a Sinful Courſe of Life. They know very well, that a Cuſtom of Sinning ſuper-induces a <hi>ſecond</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, almoſt as hard to be expell'd
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:36225:85"/>as the <hi>firſt:</hi> They are ſenſible, that the farther they proceed in any Vicious Practice, the more they are confirm'd and ſettled in it: They feel the Miſerable Chains of their Wickedneſs, and the Sad Slavery of Sin, to which they tamely Submit, and have not the Heart to make any Reſolute Attompt for their Liberty. But notwithſtanding all this, they ſtill ſuppoſe they are their own Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; they fancy that their Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is rather want of Will than Power; they perſwade themſelves, that a High and Mighty Reſolution has an Invincible Force, and that therefore they are able to reſcue themſelves from Sin and the Devil whenſoever they pleaſe. This was the Pride of all thoſe Heathen Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, who placed the Happineſs of a <hi>Wiſe Man</hi> in being Self-ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, Independent, and Supreme Diſpoſer of himſelf in all things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to make him Good and Happy. 'Twas this made <hi>Cicero</hi> ſay, <hi>Who ever gave God Thanks for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:36225:86"/>a Good Man?</hi> And this, I fear, makes many Chriſtians ſay <hi>in their Heart,</hi> whenever they do any thing that looks like good, <hi>Our own High Hand, and not our Lord, has done all this. To prepare the Way of our Lord,</hi> this <hi>Pride</hi> muſt be <hi>Humbled:</hi> This <hi>Hill</hi> muſt be <hi>brought Low:</hi> It muſt be <hi>removed</hi> out of the Way, by a ſtrong and lively Faith of our Eſſential Dependency on the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Hand that made us. All Sinners, the more they <hi>confide</hi> in their own <hi>Strength,</hi> the more they are apt to defer the time of their Repentance: But when once they are throughly convinc'd of being <hi>able to do nothing</hi> of themſelves, 'tis then that they begin to think how Dangerous it is to continue any longer in a Wicked Courſe, and to make him more and more their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, without whoſe Friendly Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance they are loſt for Ever.</p>
               <p>There are others who underſtand themſelves too well, to be ſo <hi>Proud</hi> of their own <hi>Strength.</hi> They are
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:36225:86"/>very ſenſible that in their Daily Prayers, when they ſay, <hi>Thy Will be done,</hi> they plainly acknowledge that they cannot do God's <hi>Will</hi> without his <hi>help.</hi> But their Misfortune is, that they are ſtrangely miſtaken in the Notion of his <hi>Mercy;</hi> they <hi>Preſume</hi> too much upon his <hi>Goodneſs;</hi> and expect that he ſhould help to ſave them, in ſpite of all their Faults, and without their helping them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. They are wilfully Deluded with Extravagant Idea's of God's <hi>Mercy</hi> being <hi>above all his Works,</hi> as if he regarded very little, either what we do, or what himſelf has done, but only ſtudied how to pleaſe himſelf in being <hi>Merciful</hi> to Sinners. They Perſevere as unconcern'dly in their Sins, as if the Laws of his <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> were made only to be broken, as if the Precepts of his <hi>Wiſdom</hi> were given only to be deſpiſed, and as if he took Delight in having them believe, that he is ſo unjuſtly and unreaſonably <hi>Merciful,</hi> as to Pardon them upon their own Terms, and
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:36225:87"/>let them live Sinners at their Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, that they may Die Saints at their Leiſure. They think 'tis time e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to Die to Sin, when Sin Dies to them. When Death draws near to their Bed-ſide, and ſtares them in the Face; if they can but cry <hi>Peccavi,</hi> before they feel the Fatal Stroke; if they have but time to ſay, <hi>Lord ſave us,</hi> or elſe <hi>we Periſh;</hi> 'tis enough, Our <hi>Lord</hi> is <hi>Merciful;</hi> and ſince they all along relied upon his <hi>Mercy,</hi> and ſinn'd upon that very Score, they <hi>Preſume</hi> he will not now be ſo <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmerciful,</hi> as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them in the End.</p>
               <p>Thus their <hi>Preſumption</hi> ſwells, and riſes to a moſt prodigious height; and thus it hinders their Repentance, till their <hi>Faith</hi> diſcovers how hollow the Foundation is. But then the <hi>Mountain</hi> cracks immediately; it falls to pieces in a moment; and ſinks as <hi>low</hi> as the Abyſs of its own Emptineſs. If we believe God's Word (and ſurely He knows beſt how <hi>Merciful</hi> he is) we ſoon ſhall ſee
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:36225:87"/>how Slight and Frivolous all thoſe Pretences are, on which they Build their Fooliſh Confidence. They would fain contrive ſome way or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Reconcile a Wicked Life with a Holy Death. They would willingly allow themſelves their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty in all their Vicious. Humours, and be <hi>happy</hi> their own way <hi>here;</hi> and when this is done, they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to leave the reſt to God's Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, and be <hi>happy</hi> which way he pleaſes <hi>hereafter.</hi> To pacifie their Minds, and calm their Fears, they Magnifie God's <hi>Mercy</hi> above all his other Attributes, and ſpare no Pains to Cheat themſelves into a Fond Belief, that He is much more <hi>Merciful,</hi> than he is either <hi>Wiſe</hi> or <hi>Juſt.</hi> But yet they are terribly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid, that what God cannot do <hi>juſtly</hi> and <hi>wiſely,</hi> he cannot <hi>do</hi> at all: And therefore ſome little Reaſon, or at leaſt ſome little Appearance of it, muſt be found, that they may ſeem to juſtifie their Plea for Pardon, and may have ſomething to ſay for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:36225:88"/>that the Sentence of their own Self-condemnation may not paſs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them.</p>
               <p n="1">1. There are ſome who ſeem to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume upon their Greatneſs, as if the Laws of God were only made for little Folks, and not for thoſe who are the great Law-makers of the Earth. But the <hi>Scripture</hi> aſſures us of the contrary. In the <hi>Wiſdom of Solomon</hi> we read, <hi>Hear therefore, O ye Kings and Rulers of the Earth: Your Power is given you from the Higheſt, who ſhall try your VVorks. The moſt Sharp Judgment ſhall be to them that are in High Places; and Mighty Men ſhall be mightily Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented. For God ſhall accept no Man's Perſon, nor ſtand in awe of any Man's Greatneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Others preſume upon their great Proſperity in a Wicked Life. <hi>I have ſinn'd,</hi> ſay they, <hi>and what harm has happen'd to me?</hi> But the <hi>Scripture</hi> bids them have a care of <hi>ſaying ſo;</hi> becauſe although God is <hi>patient,</hi> yet <hi>he will in no wiſe let them
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:36225:88"/>go</hi> free from Puniſhment. <hi>His In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation,</hi> ſays the Son of <hi>Sirach, has an Eye upon Sinners: Therefore be not without fear of adding Sin to Sin. Bind not one Sin upon another;</hi> but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that <hi>thou ſhalt not be unpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed in</hi> any <hi>one</hi> of them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Others preſume more fooliſhly, that in ſo great a Croud of Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, they may perhaps eſcape: I <hi>ſhall not be diſcovered,</hi> ſay they, <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſo many People; for what is my Soul amongſt ſuch an infinity of Creatures?</hi> But in the ſame <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticus</hi> we read, <hi>Number not thy ſelf among the Multitude of Sinners; but remember that his Anger will not tarry long.</hi> The longeſt delay is only till Death; and who knows how ſhort that may prove? <hi>Remember</hi> alſo that He, <hi>who Numbers all the Hairs of our Head,</hi> will as eaſily <hi>Number</hi> not only our <hi>Perſons,</hi> but our <hi>Faults.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Others preſume upon their great Donations to the Church. But this pretence is plainly Contradicted
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:36225:89"/>in <hi>Eccleſiaſticus,</hi> c. 7. <hi>Say not, God will look upon the Multitude of my Oblations, and when I offer to the moſt High God, he will accept it.</hi> No: He will not accept it: He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives no Bribes.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Others preſume upon their great Faith. But <hi>what does it profit,</hi> ſays S. <hi>James, if a Man has Faith? If he has not Works</hi> of true Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance <hi>can his Faith ſave him?</hi> No, no: <hi>He that will be ſaved,</hi> muſt <hi>keep</hi> all <hi>the Commandments,</hi> and <hi>perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere</hi> in them <hi>to the End.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Others preſume upon their much Faſting. But as the Prophet obſerves, <hi>In the Day of</hi> their <hi>Faſt,</hi> they <hi>find</hi> Pleaſure in ſeeking their <hi>own Will,</hi> and <hi>in doing their own Ways;</hi> and <hi>this is not the Faſt, which God has choſen,</hi> neither is it <hi>acceptable</hi> to him.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Others preſume upon their many Prayers. But what ſignifies Praying without Practiſing? In the <hi>Proverbs</hi> we read, <hi>He that turns away
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:36225:89"/>his Ear from hearing the Law, even his Prayer ſhall be Abomination.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. Others preſume upon their great Alms; becauſe 'tis written, that <hi>Charity covers a Multitude of Sins.</hi> But this is chiefly underſtood of our Neighbour's Sins, not ours. The <hi>covering</hi> of <hi>our own</hi> avails us nothing, unleſs we <hi>Repent, Confeſs, and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake them.</hi> 'Tis written in the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs,</hi> that <hi>He who covers his Sins, ſhall not Proſper: But whoſoever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes and forſakes them, ſhall have Mercy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. Others preſume upon their being Children of the Catholick Church. But as it was in vain for the Jews to <hi>ſay within themſelves, we have</hi> Abraham <hi>for our Father,</hi> ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe 'tis to little purpoſe for us Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks to ſay, we have the Church for our Mother. The Goſpel aſſures us, that <hi>Every Tree which brings not forth good Fruit, (Fruits worthy of true Repentance) ſhall be hewed down, and caſt into the Fire.</hi> So true it is, that there's no Ground at all for
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:36225:90"/>our <hi>Preſumption,</hi> no Pardon to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd, no Mercy to be hop'd for, without Sincere Repentance, and a thorough-paced Amendment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>When <hi>Faith</hi> has once <hi>Levell'd</hi> theſe <hi>Mountains</hi> of <hi>Preſumption</hi> and <hi>Pride,</hi> the next Affair in Hand, is to <hi>prepare the Way of our Lord,</hi> by <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it Straight.</hi> There's nothing ſo <hi>Crooked</hi> as <hi>Self-Love.</hi> It makes us <hi>Crooked</hi> in all our Ways. It in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents a Thouſand Turnings, Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and By-ways, to compaſs its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns: It never engages in any thing abroad, without contriving to bring ſomething home: It begins from it ſelf, it tends to it ſelf, it bends till both ends meet; and what can be more <hi>Crooked?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the contrary, the <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>God</hi> is <hi>Straight.</hi> It <hi>directs</hi> us in the <hi>Way of his Commandments:</hi> And leads us in a Straight Line to that Bleſſed End for which he made us. It <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares our Hearts to God,</hi> that we may
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:36225:90"/>
                  <hi>ſerve him only.</hi> It prepares us for <hi>the Kingdom of God within us;</hi> that every Loyal Heart may be the Throne of his Divine Majeſty; that all our Paſſions, Inclinations, and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, may be Faithful Subjects to him, in <hi>doing his Will on Earth, as it is done in Heaven;</hi> and that his <hi>Love</hi> may not only <hi>Live</hi> but <hi>Reign</hi> in us, and not only <hi>now</hi> but <hi>for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Love muſt begin to <hi>Live,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it begins to <hi>Reign</hi> in us. It muſt Firſt <hi>move</hi> us to <hi>Repent,</hi> before <hi>the Kingdom of God,</hi> which always <hi>is at Hand,</hi> can be Eſtabliſht in our Hearts. Our Penitential Tears will never ſufficiently <hi>prepare the Way of our Lord,</hi> unleſs <hi>the Spirit</hi> of <hi>Love</hi> begin to <hi>move the Waters.</hi> Our <hi>Self-Love</hi> may Cry its Eyes out, and almoſt break its Heart with Grief: Alas! This <hi>Crooked Love</hi> can never <hi>make the Way Straight:</hi> There's no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> who is all <hi>Truth,</hi> all <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and all <hi>Holineſs,</hi> there's nothing elſe can <hi>make</hi> all <hi>Straight,</hi> by making us <hi>truly Repent,</hi>
                  <pb n="178" facs="tcp:36225:91"/>and <hi>moving</hi> us to <hi>Deteſt</hi> and <hi>Hate</hi> all <hi>Falſhood,</hi> all <hi>Injuſtice,</hi> and all <hi>Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Trent,</hi> in the 6. ch. of the 6. <hi>Seſſion,</hi> deſcribing <hi>Repentance,</hi> ſuch as always <hi>was,</hi> and now <hi>is,</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite, as well <hi>before Baptiſm,</hi> as <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> the Sacrament of <hi>Penance,</hi> lays the whole Train of Penitential Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions in this Natural Order. It mentions, 1. Our <hi>Fear of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Juſtice;</hi> 2. Our <hi>Hope of Mercy through Chriſt;</hi> 3. Our <hi>beginning to Love God as the Fountain of all Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs;</hi> 4. Our <hi>being therefore moved with Hatred and Deteſtation of our Sins;</hi> 5. Our <hi>purpoſing to begin a New Life, by keeping the Divine Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> And again in the 4. ch. of the 14. <hi>Seſſion,</hi> the ſame Council <hi>declares,</hi> that all true Repentance <hi>includes not only a Ceſſation from Sin, but alſo a Beginning of a New Life, and a Hatred of the Old One;</hi> according to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>Caſt away from you all your Tranſgreſſions, and make you a New Heart, and a New Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="179" facs="tcp:36225:91"/>
               <p>Let us now conſider a little this Doctrine, and we ſhall find it ſo Clear and Rational, as not to need the Authority of a Council to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend it to us.</p>
               <p n="1">1. When Sinners Sleep ſecurely, they Dream of nothing but the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual Satisfactions, and the Tranſitory Pleaſures of this Life. But when they once are rouz'd, and throughly awaken'd with a Strong Belief and Lively Apprehenſion of a future State, in which God's Juſtice will Eternally deprive them of theſe things, and puniſh them ſeverely with the contrary, there's nothing more Natural, than to be ſtruck with <hi>Fear</hi> of ſuch a Puniſhment: And, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they ſee it by a Super-natural Light, they dread it with a Natural <hi>Fear.</hi> Neither is there any need of quoting <hi>Aquinas</hi> for this Truth: It being as evidently <hi>Natural</hi> to to <hi>fear</hi> the <hi>Pain of Senſe,</hi> as it is to <hi>Love</hi> the <hi>Pleaſure of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The uneaſineſs of this <hi>Fear</hi> is
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:36225:92"/>Troubleſome to us: And when 'tis great, we dare not ſhake it off, as uſually we do our Creditors, whom we refuſe to Speak with, when we have no Mind to give them Satisfaction. The <hi>Fear</hi> of being Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refted, and Eternally confin'd from all that ever pleas'd us, when it once looks Big and Terrible up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, it ſoon brings down our Stomachs, and makes us contented now, to think how Merciful God is, and ſeek for <hi>Hope</hi> of Comfort in the Merits of his Son.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When we are thus conſidering, how <hi>good</hi> God is, and how <hi>bad</hi> we are; how <hi>great</hi> his Mercy is, and how <hi>little</hi> we deſerve it; how <hi>ſevere</hi> his Juſtice is, and how <hi>much</hi> we have provok'd it: When we are wavering 'twixt <hi>Hope</hi> and <hi>Fear,</hi> and pondering the Reaſons on both ſides; admiring that Incomprehenſible Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, which moved the moſt High God to ſend his only Son for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of the World, and being Aſtoniſht at his Inexorable Juſtice,
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:36225:92"/>which would not be aton'd by any other Sacrifice: When we compare the <hi>Crookedneſs</hi> of <hi>Sin</hi> with the <hi>Straight Paths</hi> of <hi>Virtue;</hi> the <hi>Truth,</hi> the <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> and <hi>Equity</hi> of God's Laws, with our <hi>Hypocriſie, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs,</hi> and <hi>Iniquity:</hi> When we ſtudy the Charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Features of his Divine Beauty, and, in his own Light, ſee our Horrible Deformity: 'Tis then, that we <hi>begin to Love him as the Fountain of all Righteouſneſs;</hi> and, becauſe we love him, <hi>therefore</hi> we <hi>Deteſt</hi> and <hi>Hate</hi> our <hi>Sins,</hi> by which we have offended him: 'Tis then, that we are ſenſible, what Fools we have been, to <hi>forſake</hi> our <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Fountain of Living Waters,</hi> and ſeek our Happineſs amongſt his Creatures, by <hi>hewing out Ciſterns, Broken Ciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns, which can hold no Water:</hi> 'Tis then, our Heart is ready to Break with Grief, to think that <hi>we have erred from the</hi> Straight <hi>Ways of Truth, and we tried our ſelves in the</hi> Crooked <hi>Ways of Wickedneſs and Deſtruction:</hi> 'Tis then, I ſay, we firmly <hi>purpoſe
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:36225:93"/>to begin a New Life,</hi> becauſe we <hi>Hate the Old One:</hi> And then, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Prophet, we <hi>caſt away from us all our Tranſgreſſions;</hi> becauſe we have <hi>now a New Heart, and a New Spirit;</hi> we <hi>love</hi> our <hi>God,</hi> whom hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto we ſlighted; and, for his ſake, we <hi>Hate</hi> the <hi>Vices</hi> which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly we <hi>Loved,</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> the <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues</hi> which heretofore we <hi>Hated.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By what has been already ſaid, 'tis eaſie to anſwer a very Important Queſtion, <hi>Whether Sorrow ariſing from the Fear of Hell alone, may deſerve the Name of True Repentance?</hi> 'Tis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed by all, and declared in Council, That <hi>without the Sacrament of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance it cannot, of it ſelf, juſtifie a Sinner:</hi> The Queſtion is, Whether <hi>it</hi> ſufficiently <hi>diſpoſes him, in that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, to obtain the Grace of God?</hi> To avoid miſtakes in a matter of this Moment, we muſt obſerve, that in <hi>Hell</hi> there are Two ſorts of <hi>Pain,</hi> the one of <hi>Senſe,</hi> the other of <hi>Loſing</hi> God: And conſequently there muſt be alſo admitted Two ſorts of <hi>Fear</hi>
                  <pb n="183" facs="tcp:36225:93"/>and <hi>Sorrow,</hi> the one proceeding from <hi>Self-love,</hi> the other from the <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Second</hi> ſort of <hi>Sorrow,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it falls ſhort of <hi>Perfect Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition,</hi> yet nevertheleſs it pre-ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes a <hi>Fear</hi> of loſing God's Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in this World, and his Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in the next, a <hi>deſire</hi> to pleaſe him here, and to enjoy him hereafter, an actual <hi>Love</hi> of him, as our laſt End, and chiefeſt Good: And ſince their <hi>Love, Deſire,</hi> and <hi>Fear,</hi> may be ſo great, as to imply a Preference of him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all his Creatures, it follows clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the <hi>Sorrow,</hi> which is ground on this <hi>Love,</hi> may poſſibly <hi>exclude</hi> all Actual <hi>Deſire of Sinning;</hi> which if it does, the Council tell us, That <hi>it is an Impulſe of the Holy Spirit, not yet dwelling in us, but moving us, by which a Penitent prepares the way for his being juſtified.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the <hi>Firſt</hi> ſort of <hi>Sorrow</hi> is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly inſufficient; and 'tis very fit that we ſhould know it in good time, before we feel it. And that we may
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:36225:94"/>diſcern what ground our <hi>Sorrow</hi> goes upon, S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> thus propoſes the Caſe, in his 19. Sermon, <hi>de ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis Apoſtoli; Behold,</hi> ſays he, <hi>the Lord your God tries you, as who ſhould ſay, Do what you will; and whatſoever pleaſes you, take it for granted that 'tis lawful; I do not Puniſh it; I do not caſt you into Hell for it; only I ſhall</hi> certainly <hi>deny you</hi> the Sight of <hi>my Face for ever. If you were afraid; you Loved.</hi> If you are more <hi>afraid</hi> of this, than any other thing; you Love him above all things. Your <hi>Love</hi> inſpires you with a Noble <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation</hi> of all Sin, a Strong <hi>Averſion</hi> againſt it, a Continual <hi>Fear</hi> of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring God's Diſpleaſure by it, and a True Penitential <hi>Sorrow</hi> for having been Guilty of it. But if you Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue not the <hi>Loſs</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> if you are unconcern'd for all the Joys of his Bleſt Company; if you neither Care for Him nor his Heaven, provided he allows you all your Pleaſures up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth; you may be very well aſſured, that as long as you <hi>Love</hi> your
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:36225:94"/>Humour, Eaſe, and Pleaſure, above all things, your <hi>Fear</hi> and <hi>Sorrow</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding purely from this <hi>Love,</hi> can never of themſelves <hi>exclude</hi> your Actual <hi>Deſire of Sinning.</hi> This very <hi>Love</hi> is a Capital Sin, which Breeds a Thouſand <hi>Deſires of Sinning:</hi> And, according to the eagerneſs of thoſe Deſires, the greater is your <hi>Fear,</hi> that they will all be Diſappointed, and ſeverely Puniſht; and the greater is your <hi>Sorrow,</hi> to think that all God's Penal Laws againſt theſe Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal <hi>Deſires,</hi> will certainly be put in Execution for all Eternity. The <hi>Fear</hi> of <hi>Senſible Pain,</hi> and the <hi>Deſire</hi> of <hi>Sinful Pleaſure,</hi> grow naturally both upon the ſame Stock; they are both rooted in the ſame <hi>Self-love:</hi> And how then can the <hi>one</hi> be able, of it ſelf, to pull up the <hi>other</hi> by the Roots? How can the <hi>Fear</hi> of <hi>Pain</hi> extirpate the <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>Pleaſure,</hi> and <hi>exclude</hi> the <hi>Will,</hi> or the <hi>Deſire,</hi> of <hi>Sinning?</hi> For this Reaſon, S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> in his Book <hi>againſt the Adverſaries of the Law,</hi> affirms, That <hi>the Deſire of
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:36225:95"/>doing ill is not excluded, but by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Deſire of doing well.</hi> And in his <hi>Epiſtle</hi> 144. he ſays, <hi>In vain does he think himſelf a Conquerour of Sin, who abſtains from it only for Fear of Pain: For although he does not out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly Accompliſh his Wicked Deſire, yet this Deſire, this Enemy of his, is ſtill within him. He who fears Hell, does not fear Sinning, but Burning.</hi> Alas! This <hi>Servile</hi> and <hi>Carnal</hi> Fear, as S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> calls it, can never <hi>change</hi> the <hi>Heart:</hi> It can never <hi>alter</hi> our <hi>Minds:</hi> Becauſe as long as we <hi>fear</hi> nothing but <hi>Burning,</hi> we are every <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as <hi>carnally-minded</hi> as before; we <hi>mind</hi> nothing but the Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our <hi>Senſes;</hi> this we <hi>love,</hi> this we <hi>deſire;</hi> and by the ſame Rule are <hi>Afraid</hi> and <hi>Sorry,</hi> when we think of <hi>Pain</hi> and <hi>Torment. To be carnally-minded is Death,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle; <hi>but, to be ſpiritually-minded, is Life and Peace.</hi> Our <hi>Repentance</hi> is not <hi>true,</hi> unleſs it <hi>change</hi> our <hi>Hearts,</hi> and make us <hi>ſpiritually-minded:</hi> It muſt <hi>make to us a New Heart, and a
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:36225:95"/>New Spirit:</hi> It muſt make us <hi>Love</hi> a <hi>New Life,</hi> and <hi>therefore Hate</hi> the <hi>Old One.</hi> Our <hi>Hatred</hi> of <hi>this,</hi> is always grounded in the <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>that;</hi> and, as S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſays in his <hi>Epiſtle</hi> 144. <hi>So much as we Love</hi> the one, <hi>ſo much we Hate</hi> the other. <hi>O how I Loved thy Law!</hi> Says the Pſalmiſt; <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I Hated every Evil Way.</hi> In a Word, The <hi>Love of God muſt prepare the Way of our Lord,</hi> becauſe <hi>Self-love</hi> is <hi>Crooked,</hi> and can <hi>therefore</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>make it Straight.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>S. <hi>Paul</hi> in his Second Epiſtle to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> humbly and hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begs, that <hi>our Lord may direct our Hearts in the Love of God, and in the Patience of Chriſt.</hi> And 'tis a moſt Excellent Prayer. For when once the <hi>Love of God</hi> has <hi>made the Way Straight,</hi> there's nothing wanting but the <hi>Patience of Chriſt</hi> to <hi>make it Smooth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. The Apoſtle aſſures us, we <hi>have need of Patience to do the Will of God;</hi>
                  <pb n="188" facs="tcp:36225:96"/>to Fight, and Conquer, and Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain our Conqueſt to the End. Self-love and Pride, the Mortal Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of our Eternal Happineſs, can never quite Die, as long as we our ſelves are Living; they lodge in our very Boſoms; we cannot hinder their <hi>Living</hi> and <hi>Moving</hi> in us; we cannot prevent the Firſt Rebellious Inſurrections of them: But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, we can prevent being Surprized by them, we can always be upon our Guard, we can throw them as faſt as they Riſe; and we have this great Comfort left, that every Fall Weakens them, and every Victory Encreaſes our Power over them, till at length they make ſo Small and Feeble a Reſiſtance, that thoſe very Conflicts, which at firſt were Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to us, now become a pleaſing Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, which ſeems to be the Sport and Paſtime, rather than the Trial, of our Virtue. This Degree of <hi>Patience</hi> is the ſureſt Mark of <hi>true Repentance.</hi> 'Tis certain we are not <hi>truly Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent,</hi> unleſs we abſolutely and fully
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:36225:96"/>reſolve to <hi>Decline from Evil,</hi> and to <hi>Do Good:</hi> And though this Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution may ſeem Strong and Firm, yet we ſhall ſoon diſcover its Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; we ſhall preſently Break it, if we have not <hi>Patience</hi> to keep it. The longer we have liv'd in Sin, the ſtronger are our Vicious Habits, the harder it is to ſtruggle with them; the more Pains we muſt take to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter them, and therefore ſo much greater <hi>Patience</hi> is requiſite to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them. But whatſoever diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties we may meet with by the Way, we muſt remember, that theſe Obſtacles which give us ſo much Trouble, are the Work of our own Hands. Our Sinful Habits are the woful Fruit of our own wilful Wickedneſs. The <hi>Crookedneſs</hi> and <hi>Roughneſs</hi> of our Nature was Soft and Tender at firſt: If our Reaſon had begun betimes to make it <hi>Straight</hi> and <hi>Smooth,</hi> it had been done with eaſe: And whoſe Fault was it, that we did not riſe, and fall to Work, at a more Early Hour?
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:36225:97"/>Since therefore the Fault is our own, we have no Reaſon to Complain, and Grumble at the Hardſhip of our Labour. If we cannot now per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form our Work without the Sweat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our Brows, and Aking of our Hearts, we may Thank our own <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption</hi> and <hi>Self-love,</hi> which were the Sad Occaſion of ſuch long delays; and therefore we have Reaſon to have <hi>Patience</hi> with our ſelves.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We <hi>have need of Patience,</hi> not only <hi>to do the Will of God,</hi> but alſo <hi>to ſuffer it.</hi> We need it, not only to <hi>do good,</hi> but to <hi>endure</hi> whatever <hi>Evils</hi> he ſhall pleaſe to appoint us. 'Tis not ſufficient to <hi>begin a New Life:</hi> We muſt alſo <hi>Hate the Old One,</hi> and be willing to undergo the juſt Puniſhments of it. There's nothing ſo effectual, as a true Senſe of our Guilt, to make us truly <hi>Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent.</hi> An <hi>Humble Penitent</hi> is throughly convinc'd, that all the Sufferings of this Momentary Life, are nothing to what he deſerves. He thinks himſelf unworthy of the Ground he
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:36225:97"/>goes upon. He knows that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves to have it Open under him, and Swallow him Alive. He does not look upon himſelf as Pardon'd, but Repriev'd; and therefore Trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles at the Dreadful Apprehenſion of Unſpeakable and Everlaſting Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, which he ſtill fears may be his Doom at laſt. He <hi>fears not them who Kill the Body, and are not able to Kill the Soul;</hi> but, from theſe Words of our Saviour, he learns to <hi>fear him</hi> only <hi>who is able to Deſtroy both Soul and Body in Hell.</hi> The Fear of <hi>Hell</hi> Sinks deeply in his Mind, as Deep as the Abyſs it ſelf, and Swallows up all other little Fears of <hi>Momentary Pains.</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd to <hi>Hell,</hi> they are <hi>no more</hi> than the leaſt <hi>Drop</hi> of Water to the <hi>Ocean;</hi> nor yet <hi>ſo much,</hi> becauſe the ſmalleſt Drop has ſtill ſome ſmall Proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the Sea, whereas thoſe <hi>Pains</hi> have <hi>leſs</hi> Proportion with thoſe, and <hi>Time</hi> has <hi>none at all</hi> with our <hi>Eternity.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore an <hi>Humble Penitent,</hi> whatever happens to him, he ſubmits not only
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:36225:98"/>willingly, but cheerfully: He Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly Kiſſes the kind Hand which lays the Croſs upon his Shoulders; and thankfully acknowledges the Double Favour of God's Infinite Mercy, who is pleas'd not only to Exchange his Many and Everlaſting Torments, for a few Tranſitory Afflictions, but alſo to Reward his <hi>Little</hi> and <hi>Short</hi> Sufferings, with <hi>a far more Exceeding and Eternal Weight of Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>We have need of Patience,</hi> not only <hi>to Suffer the Will of God</hi> in theſe unuſual Trials; but alſo <hi>to Bear one another's Burdens,</hi> and to Support the uneaſie Humours of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, in all common Occaſions. That Heroick Patience is the proper Character of Confeſſors and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs: This belongs to all good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; it concerns us all, and every one of us. All our <hi>Impatience</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Selfiſhneſs,</hi> which make us Love our Honour, Intereſt, and Humour, better than God and our Neighbour. When we are Contradicted, Slighted, or Deſpiſed, our Patience has much ado
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:36225:98"/>to keep us quiet, our Blood Riſes, our Spirits are Ruffled and Diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, our Thoughts are in a Hurry, to lay hold on ſome Revenge or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and without the leaſt Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, catch at any thing that's uppermoſt or neareſt Hand. Is this the Natural Temper of an <hi>Humble Mind?</hi> Surely, although we ſtand in our own Light, we are not ſo much in the Dark, but we can ſee, or feel at leaſt, that theſe Reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Diſturbances proceed from <hi>Pride,</hi> and that they are all Rooted in <hi>Self-love.</hi> We <hi>Love</hi> our <hi>Honour</hi> becauſe we <hi>Love</hi> our <hi>Selves:</hi> And, for the ſelf-ſame Reaſon, we Love a Thouſand other things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides our <hi>Honour;</hi> all thoſe things, I mean, which fall under theſe two Heads, our <hi>Intereſt</hi> and our <hi>Pleaſure.</hi> Our <hi>Intereſt</hi> is liable to an Infinity of Various Accidents, which Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble our Temporal Affairs; our <hi>Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi> is the Object of as many Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent and unreaſonable Humours; and every little Gale of Wind, that
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:36225:99"/>blows Croſs to the <hi>one</hi> or <hi>other,</hi> is enough to raiſe a Storm, in which our <hi>Patience</hi> ſeldom fails to ſuffer Shipwrack. For this Reaſon, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever I ſee a Cholerick Perſon grow <hi>Patient,</hi> I look upon it as an Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Sign of his being <hi>truly Penitent.</hi> When I ſee him <hi>caſt away from him all his</hi> uſual Motions of <hi>Impatience,</hi> I eaſily imagine that he has <hi>made to himſelf a New Heart and a New Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi> When I obſerve him Eaſie and Cheerful, not withſtanding any Slights or Provocations: When I diſcover a calm and even Temper in him, in Spite of any Croſſes or Diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments: When I perceive him as ready to Excuſe or Over-look an Injury, as he was before to Aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate it, or Revenge it: Then indeed I have juſt Reaſon to conclude, he is no longer govern'd by the <hi>Spirit of this World,</hi> but that he is <hi>renew'd</hi> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, <hi>in the Spirit of his Mind,</hi> and <hi>led by the Spirit of God, the Love of God, and Patience of Chriſt.</hi> The very word <hi>Repentance,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:36225:99"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
